<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Essaies politicke, and morall. By D.T. Gent</title>
            <author>D. T. (Daniel Tuvill), d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 134 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853996</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853996</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19401</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14087)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19401)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 726:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Essaies politicke, and morall. By D.T. Gent</title>
                  <author>D. T. (Daniel Tuvill), d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 130, [2] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H[umphrey] L[ownes] for Mathew Lownes, dvvelling in Paules Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>D.T. = Daniel Tuvill.</note>
                  <note>Erroneously attributed to John Tovey.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature mark "A."; the last two leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſſaies</hi> POLITICKE, and <hi>MORALL.</hi> By <hi>D. T.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Humphrey Lownes, a compartment featuring two angels or cherubs with Lancashire and Yorkshire roses at the top, and a lion and dragon separated by a corinthian column at the bottom (not in McKerrow)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed By <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Mathew Lownes,</hi> dvvelling in Paules Churchyard. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:2"/>
            <head>The chiefe Heads, handled in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Of Perſwaſion: wherin is diſcourſed
<list>
                     <item>Of Opinion.</item>
                     <item>Of Affection.</item>
                     <item>Of The force of Reaſon.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Of Prayſes.</item>
               <item>Of Paines, and Induſtrie.</item>
               <item>Of cautions in Friendſhip.</item>
               <item>Of three thinges prejudiciall to Secrecie.</item>
               <item>Of Reputation.</item>
               <item>Of Accuſation.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and vertuous LADIE, the Ladie <hi>Anne Harington.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The deſire I had to manifest my ſeruicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble affection towards your Honour in outwarde Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, hath on ſuch idle houres, as remained free to mee from your imployments, begot this young and tender Infant; whom I preſum'd, vpon his birth (beeing yet an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio</hi> in his fathers braine) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote, &amp; conſecrate wholly to your honourable Selfe, as to the chiefe,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:3"/>and finall end of his beeing. His ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie is not of the weakest: and therefore, howſoeuer hee may now ſeeme altogether vnfaſhion'd, I make no doubt, but by converſing with your Ladiſhip (whoſe boſome the hand of heauen hath ſo richlie furniſht with all exemplary ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, that from among ſo many, Wiſdome ſelected you, to be the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſſe, from whom the Princely iſſue of a royall bed might receiue instruction) his ruder ignorance may be reduced to a better forme. <hi>Eſſaies</hi> are the things hee vttereth. His yeeres deny him that length of breath, which ſhould enable him to holde out in a continued, and long diſcourſe. My ſelfe haue imparted vnto him, part of that beauty and
<pb facs="tcp:19401:3"/>Perfection, which Art, &amp; Nature hath bestowed on me. Such therfore as he is, I preſent him to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours view; who, I hope, will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorde him ſuch worthy entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as may hold ſome euen corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondencie, with his deſires, as well as his deſerts. And ſo in the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest degree of ſervice, that either loue, or dutifull obſervance can imagine, I kiſſe your Honourable handes; deſirous of nothing more, then alwaies to be reputed,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>Your Honors moſt affectionate ſeruant, <hi>D. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19401:4"/>
            <head>Of Perſwaſion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ground a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of what nature ſoeuer, in the hearts of a publique Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, there are three things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily required: The one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the opinion had of the partie perſwading: The other, in the affection of the parties to be perſwaded: and the laſt, in the perſpicuitie, and ſoundneſſe of the reaſon it ſelfe, by which hee
<pb facs="tcp:19401:5"/>labours to perſwade them. As concerning the firſt, it was thought by the Magiſtrates of <hi>Sparta,</hi> to be a matter of ſo great importance, that when they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued one of looſe, &amp; diſſolute behauior, ready to propounde vnto the people, an aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the approbation whereof, they knew, would be no ſmal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement to the good, &amp; quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their State, &amp; Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, they did immediatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (fearing, it ſhold ſeeme, leaſt his known manners might haue preiudic't the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the thing) and intreated one, who for his graue &amp; vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous carriage, was of ſome honor and reputation amongſt them, to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19401:5"/>take vpon him the invention, &amp; to deliuer it vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as if it had proceeded meerly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelfe. And it hath bin alwaies the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of wiſer <hi>States-men,</hi> for the better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſing of exaſperated minds, whither it were in the blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die factions of the greater, or in the tumultuous broyles of the meaner, to chuſe ſom one whoſe graue repreſentation, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with a remarquable, honeſt, and vertuous diſpoſition, might vpon his very firſt approch, work an awful reſpect towards his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp; withal a reuerend attentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towards his words, in the hearts and mindes of ſuch as ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him. For there are not any ſo mutinous &amp; turbulent aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:6"/>howſoeuer they may ſeem to conſiſt of thoſe actiue &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſpirites, <hi>quibus quieta mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere,</hi> as <hi>Salus</hi> ſaid of ſome of his time, <hi>magna merces videtur:</hi> that thinke the very diſturbance of things eſtabliſhed, a ſufficient hyre to ſet them on worke, but will ſome-what (though incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Paſſions arme them with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo deſperate a reſolution, to effect their miſchieuous projects and deſignes) honour the ſight &amp; preſence of ſuch a one: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when they think he is not intereſted in the cauſe, or indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by any priuate obligation, to ſeek the good of the one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with any hurt, or diſaduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the other: but that his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19401:6"/>loue and affection, doth equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie border vpon both, &amp; that the reducing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a peaceable agreement of their differences for the publique good, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the State, is the chiefeſt, and onelie marke he aymes at: and this was excellentlie deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the Poet, when he ſaid,</p>
            <q>
               <l>— <hi>Magno in populo cùm ſaepè coorta eſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seditio, ſaeuit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> animis ignobile vulgus:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> faces, et ſaxa volant: furor arma mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pietate graue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac meritis, ſi fortè viru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conspexêre, ſilent: arrectiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> auribus adſtant.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>And for this cauſe it hath been a cuſtom among the Spanyards, to make choice of <hi>Church-men</hi> for the better managing of ſuch buſineſſes: yea, they haue beene often-times imploy'd by him in
<pb facs="tcp:19401:7"/>matters of treaty, with an intent and purpoſe, to lende a greater Maieſtie to his negotiations, and more feinedly to colour his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til fetches &amp; deuices: as when for the aſſurance of his new-got co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> he ſent 2. <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliers</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> to talke with the Queene about a peace, who by reaſon of the credit their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion had gain'd them, returned homewards with no ill ſucceſſe. Whereas if they be men of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering fame, that haue the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch affaires, their reaſons, be they neuer ſo appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly good, doe lightlie ſerue to no better vſe, then to ſharpen and ſtirre vp the ill-affected humours of their crazie mindes the more; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19401:7"/>in the end, themſelues becom a ſubiect for their diſtempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to worke vpon: eſpeciallie, when that ſmal ſparkle of <hi>Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding</hi> (which is vſually the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vulgar) is dimm'd, &amp; obſcur'd with any miſt of preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, or clowde of <hi>Paſsionate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi> And the reaſon hereof is, the ſhallow ignorance of a waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and vnſteadie multitude, which beeing for the moſt part led to iudge of matters onely by a <hi>Senſitiue apprehenſion</hi> they haue of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; not able of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to looke further into the depth of things, then the ſuperficiall bark will ſuffer the eye of their exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Senſe</hi> to winde it ſelfe into them, doe often times by reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:19401:8"/>thereof growe iealous euen of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue</hi> it ſelfe; as the manie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iles, and <hi>Oſtraciſmes</hi> practiced in thoſe <hi>Democraticall,</hi> and <hi>Popular</hi> ſtates of elder times can ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlie witneſſe: and therfore are the more to be excuſed, if they ſuſpect the ends and purpoſes of ſuch, as are not knowne to them at all, or not knowne to them at leaſt for any eminent good qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity that is in them, but rather for the contrarie; it beeing an <hi>Axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome</hi> approoued of moſt men, that <hi>Malus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Publius.</note> 
               <hi>vbi bonum ſe ſimulat, tunc est peſsimus.</hi> So that howſoeuer good Wine let not to be good by beeing poured out of an earthen veſſell: yet to preſent a whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome medicine, to a weaker ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19401:8"/>in an vnhandſome box, is to the grieued Patient oft-times a cauſe of diſeaſe; and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, may fall out to bee a meanes of vtter refuſall. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Good thinges looſe the grace of their goodneſſe, when in good &amp; conuenient maner they be not performed: and ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when by good and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient perſons they bee not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 20. <hi>ver:</hi> 19.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſum ſemel principem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ſeu benè, ſeu malè facta pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munt.</hi> A Prince, after hee hath once incurr'd the hatred and ill opinion of his ſubiects, and by ſome one particular bad action or other, alienated &amp; eſtranged
<pb facs="tcp:19401:9"/>their affections from him, ſhall find the glory of whatſoeuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize he ſhal vndertake, to be blaſted eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the very bloſſom, by ſome ſiniſter and ſcandalous interpretation: neither will the lawfulnes, or goodneſſe of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, be a ſufficient plea, to preuent it from being burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vnto him. For the illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, I need produce no other inſtance then that of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellius,</hi> who as <hi>Tacitus</hi> reports, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his entrance into <hi>Rome, Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infimae plebis rumore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> affectabat,</hi> endeuord, all he could, to mark &amp; faſhion out his actions, by the ſquare and rule of <hi>Popular appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation,</hi> doing many things, which had they proceeded from a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19401:9"/>ground, would haue been receiued as pleaſing, &amp; accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but in him, <hi>memoriâ vitae pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oris, indecora et vilia accipieba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur,</hi> by the memory of his fore-ſpent life, they were of moſt men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted as diſhonorable, &amp; baſe. <hi>Tiberius,</hi> when <hi>Spaniſh Adulation</hi> wold haue erected a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to the perpetual honor of his name, did moſt earneſtly oppoſe himſelfe againſt their determination, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in open Senat: <hi>Ego me P. C.</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>mortale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſse, et hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> officia fungi ſatiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> habere, ſi locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> principe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> impleam, et vos testor, et meminiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe posteros volo: qui ſatis, ſuper<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> memoriae meae tribuent, vt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioribus meis dignum, rerum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strarum providum, constantem
<pb facs="tcp:19401:10"/>in periculis, offenſionum pro vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate publicâ non pavidum credant: haec mihi in animis veſtris templa, hae pulcherrimae effigies, et manſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae:</hi> That I am mortall, and that I vndergoe the offices of humane frailtie, and that it ſufficeth me, if I can performe the place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I am called, I take you to witneſſe, O choſen Senators, and I would poſteritie ſhould bee mindfull of it, who ſhall ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently honour my remembrance, when they are perſwaded, that I am woorthie my Anceſtors, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident in your affaires, conſtant in dangers, and careleſſe of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, where queſtion is of the publique good. Theſe ſhall be to me thoſe honorable temples,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19401:10"/>and thoſe excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtatues, which once grounded in your mindes, ſhall remaine for euer: whereof one ſaith, they were <hi>praeclara verba, ſed non pro Tiberio:</hi> they were excellent words, had they beene vttered by an excellent man: but proceeding from him, they ſerued but to aggrauate, &amp; make worſe, the fore-conceiued ſuſpicion they had of his diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling carriage.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe, <hi>Legi à ſe militem, non emi,</hi> ſaid <hi>Galba:</hi> whereof <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> ſpeaking, ſaith it was <hi>Vox pro Repub. honeſta, ſed ipſi anceps,</hi> an honeſt, and well-beſeeming voyce in regard of the common wealth, but doubtfull in reſpect of himſelfe. <hi>Nec enim ad hanc for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam
<pb facs="tcp:19401:11"/>caetera erant:</hi> for the reſt of his life was not agreeable heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. And hence it is, that the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of heauen, ſpeaking by the mouth of <hi>Timothie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Epiſ.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 19.</note> warneth eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that calleth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iniquitie: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Non eſt enim,</hi> ſaith <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philact, ſpecioſalaus in ore peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> And this is the reaſon why <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe in <hi>Mark</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 25. rebuked the vncleane ſpirit, and commaunded him to hold his peace, euen then, when hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed him to bee <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the holy one of God:</hi> &amp; why <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16. <hi>ver.</hi> 18.</note> beeing vexed with the praiſes, and commendations of the <hi>Pythoniſt,</hi> who folowing him,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19401:11"/>and his company, continually cryed out, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>theſe men are the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the most high God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>who make knowne vnto vs the way of ſaluation,</hi> commanded the ſpirit to come forth of her, <hi>quaſi nolens ſanctus ab immundo ore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</hi> Neither was it without reaſon, that a graue &amp; wiſe Philoſopher of former times, ſuſpected the vprightnes of his owne carriage, when hee heard himſelfe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by one, whoſe life and converſation was of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtrayne. How then can thoſe impious, thoſe irreligious and Phariſaicall <hi>Levites</hi> of this corrupted and depraued age,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:12"/>free the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from thoſe aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and imputations, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the leaſt diſcerning iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (ſuch is the palpableneſſe of their irregular enormities) may bee iuſtlie caſt vpon them; for that notwithſtanding the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth &amp; Knowledge hath enobled them ſo farre, as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title them the Salt of the earth (where-with whatſoeuer is not ſeaſoned, is fatuous &amp; vnſauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) and graced the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſo high a vocation, as is the diſpenſation of his heauenly myſteries, doe runne themſelues breathleſſe in a courſe of life, which is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſproportionable to the grounds and principles of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> derogating therby not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19401:12"/>from the excellencie and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of his celeſtiall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Word? For whence is it, that prophane <hi>Atheiſme</hi> hath taken ſuch ſure footing in the hearts of ignorant, and ſimple men; who for the moſt part beeing vnable to iudge, or conceiue of vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalities, ſuffer themſelues (as I ſaid before) to be wholly guided by their externall ſenſe, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the boundleſſe diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſome <hi>Church-men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 24.</note> who practiſe not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, that which they propound to others.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I cannot chooſe but commend his policie, who hauing converted a <hi>Iew</hi> a friend of his, to <hi>Christianitie,</hi> &amp; percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him preſentlie after deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb facs="tcp:19401:13"/>for his better ſatisfaction to goe to <hi>Rome,</hi> laboured by all meanes to diſſwade him from it; fearing, leaſt the corrupt, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered manners of the Clergie there, might haue wrought in him ſome diſlike of the <hi>Religion,</hi> &amp; ſo by conſequence haue moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him to turne <hi>Jew</hi> againe. So that whoſoeuer would effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly work vpon the minds of men, with aduantage to himſelfe, hee muſt not onely ſay well, but doe well alſo. <hi>Facta mea, non dicta vos milites ſequi volo, nec diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinam modo, ſed exemplum etiam à me petere, qui hâc dextrâ mihi tres Conſulatus, ſummamque lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem peperi;</hi> ſaide <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus</hi> to his ſouldiors, when they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19401:13"/>were to march againſt the <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites.</hi> The very ayre and Eccho of which wordes, according to the apprehenſion my ſelfe haue of them, was ſufficient to haue breath'd a warlike motion, and reſolution, into the very ſteele where-with their hands were ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and made the paleſt-liuerd wretch amongſt them, ſuddainly Conquerour.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, he that thinks much the wordes of his mouth ſhould be neglected, hee muſt ſo carrie himſelfe, that his deedes may be alwaies readie to giue authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and countenance to his words: yea there muſt not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing in him, or about him, but what may work a wondrous
<pb facs="tcp:19401:14"/>admiration of him in the hearers eye, and a zealous imitation of him in his heart: finallie, he muſt haue in him thoſe three tongues whereof the <hi>Scripture</hi> maketh mention; and which are founde in euery well-diſpoſed naturall man. The firſt is the tongue of the heart: <hi>Qui loquitur verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem in Corde ſuo. Pſalm.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 2. The other is the tongue of the mouth; <hi>Qui non egit dolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guâ ſuâ. v.</hi> 3. The third and laſt, is the tongue of our workes; whereof <hi>Christ</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Opera quae ego facio, testimoniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perhibent de me:</hi> and whereat Saint <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptist</hi> aym'd, when after the Iewes had ſent their deputies to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19401:14"/>enquire of him what hee was, his aunſwere to them firſt was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether negatiue, to wit, that hee was not <hi>Christ,</hi> that hee was not <hi>Elias,</hi> that he was not a Prophet; till conſtrained by their impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunacie, to tell them poſitiuelie what he was, he ſaid vnto them: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>I am the voyce of him that cryeth in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert.</hi> Shewing thereby, that his whole courſe of life, was but a tongue; the particular actions whereof were ſo many ſeuerall voyces, which with a ſilent <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick,</hi> did moſt apparantly make knowne the ſoundneſſe, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cereneſſe of that infallible truth which he was ſent to teach. So that without the helpe and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb facs="tcp:19401:15"/>of this laſt, all the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, perſwaſions, encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and inſtructions, that can poſſibly be produc't by any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be they neuer ſo good, can little or nothing preuaile. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was it, that God himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to ſend <hi>Jſaias</hi> abroad to preach, hee did firſt of all, to purifie his lips, touch them with a coale from the Altar: and that to encourage <hi>Jeremie,</hi> hee ſaide vnto him; <hi>Antequa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exires de vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uâ, ſanctificaui te. Spiritu princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pali confirma me Deus:</hi> eſtabliſh me, O God, ſaith the kingly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, by thy free ſpirit, and then <hi>docebo iniquos vias tuas;</hi> I wil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the wicked in thy waies: <hi>et impij convertentur ad te:</hi> and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19401:15"/>ſhall bee converted vnto thee. Wherefore, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: thou that takeſt vppon thee to reforme the manners of others, redreſſe thine owne, that thou mayſt free both thy ſelfe, and that which thou vttereſt, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the traducements and detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a vulgar ignorance; and that it may not be ſaid of thee:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Clodius accuſat moechos, Catilina Cethegum.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>For then ſhalt thou be able to graft a perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of whatſoeuer thou ſhalt deliuer, in the mindes of thy Auditors.</p>
            <p>It is an excellent harmony, and I knowe not if vnparallell'd by that concent of <hi>Spheares;</hi> to ſee the words of men accompanied
<pb facs="tcp:19401:16"/>with their thoughts, &amp; followed by their deedes: and beſides, there is a naturall inclination in all men, to learne the <hi>Theorie,</hi> of ſuch as they know to haue beene excellent in the <hi>Practike.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hannibal</hi> will but ſcorne the Philoſopher that takes vpon him in his preſence to diſcourſe of <hi>War:</hi> &amp; <hi>Cleomenes</hi> will account that <hi>Orator</hi> but a chattering <hi>Swallowe,</hi> that ſhall preſume (he beeing by) to deſcribe the office and dutie of a <hi>Generall:</hi> the like happens to thoſe depraued and exulcerated mindes,</p>
            <q>
               <l>— <hi>qui de virtute locuti</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>clunem agitant</hi> —</l>
            </q>
            <p>For who can with patience en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to heare <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itellius</hi> preach
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19401:16"/>againſt intemperancie: or <hi>Grac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> complaine of ſeditious and mutinous aſſemblies? <hi>Manus, quae ſordes abluit, mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da eſſe debet;</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Gregorie:</hi> and therefore,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quis coelum terris non miſceat, et mare coelo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si fur displiceat Verri, aut homicida Miloni?</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Wherefore let euery man (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) ſo runne,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 27.</note> that he may obtaine; ſo fight, that hee may not beate the ayre: but as in other things, ſo likewiſe in this, bee followers of his example: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>I beate downe my bodie, and bring it into ſubiection; least after I haue prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to others, my ſelfe ſhould bee reprooued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Vespaſian,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe <hi>antiquo cultu, victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19401:17"/>he was to the Romans <hi>praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puus adstricti moris author,</hi> euen then when riot and exceſſe were the onely Stewards that atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them in publique &amp; priuate meetings. <hi>Obſequium enim inde in Principem, et aemulandi amor validior quàm poena ex legibus, et metus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tacitus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And hence it came, that <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoric</hi> King of the <hi>Goths</hi> writ vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Romane Senate in this manner: <hi>Facilius est errare natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> it is eaſier for Nature to erre, <hi>qùam diſsimilem ſui Princeps poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit Remp: formare,</hi> then that a Prince ſhould frame a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth vnlike vnto himſelfe: ſo much availeable with inferiours, is the force of an example in any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19401:17"/>perſon of authority. But if I may lawfully, &amp; without offence op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my weaknes againſt Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, I will briefly ſhowe him, that his opinion doth in ſom ſort me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradiction. For, <hi>Sylla</hi> being a diſordered liuer, made his Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens reformed: and <hi>Lyſander</hi> on the contrarie, polluted his with vices, where-with himſelfe was no way blemiſhed.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:19401:18"/>
               <head>Of Affection.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Second thing to help and further <hi>Perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> is <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection:</hi> vvhich being once tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly wrought and ſetled in the hearts and mindes of a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, &amp; that ſpecially through a good opinion conceiued of the Partie perſwading, is ſufficient of it ſelfe, though the matter which is propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded be neuer ſo weak, &amp; the reaſons that ſhould vſher it neuer ſo lame, to make an eaſie &amp; ſpeedie paſſage for it through
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19401:18"/>all the oppoſitions, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of any deeper diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit whatſoeuer. Witnes <hi>Piſistratus,</hi> who beeing brought (according to his own appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) in a Chariot to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-place, and there hauing in the ſight of all men, charged o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with thoſe woundes which his own hands had wrought: <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> could come and tel him, that he did not rightly counterfet the perſon of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes;</hi> for the <hi>Itha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> intent was, onely to beguile his foes: whereas what hee did, was to deceiue his friends: but he could not preuent him for all this, from beeing followed by the people; ſo great a commiſerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards himſelfe, &amp; ſo wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:19401:19"/>an indignation towards his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, had the viewe of thoſe ſelfe-made hurts effected in the hearts of the vulgar: who, not diſcouering the depth of his deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes (nor yet conſidering with themſelues, that the deſire of Soueraignty and rule, is ſo great in the mindes of ambitious men, that they will not ſticke to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it at the higheſt rate the Heauens can holde it at) gaue ſentence in his behalfe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the apprehenſion they had of that bloodie obiect, which was before their eyes.</p>
               <p>And the reaſon heereof is not farre from hand. For Paſſions are certaine internall acts, and operations of our ſoule, which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19401:19"/>beeing ioyned and linked in a moſt inviolable, and long-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued league of friendſhip with the ſenſitiue power, and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thereof, doe conſpire toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like diſobedient and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Subiects, to ſhake off the yoake of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and exempt themſelues from her commaund &amp; controlement, that they may ſtill exerciſe thoſe diſordered motions, in this contract world of our frayle and humaine bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which during her nonage or minoritie, they were accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to doe. And for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter effecting heereof, they doe firſt of all (through the helpe of a corrupt imagination) ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the <hi>Wit,</hi> and aftervvardes
<pb facs="tcp:19401:20"/>vpon the <hi>Will,</hi> which harbouring in it ſelfe two diuers inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: the one to follow <hi>Reaſon</hi> as her Soueraigne; the other to content the <hi>Senſes</hi> as her friends, is eaſilie brought (being by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corrupted, &amp; bribed with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) intirely to loue the one, &amp; vtterly to leaue and forſake the other: or at leaſt, like a careleſſe Magiſtrat (who, for the auoiding of ſom particular mens diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, neglects the good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Common-weale) to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that care, which as <hi>Gouerneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Soule,</hi> ſhe is bound in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to haue ouer it: loathing to ſee the quietnes of her owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate interrupted by the diuided factions, and tumultuous partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19401:20"/>of inferior miniſters; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when ſhee perceiues the ſoule to be partaker likewiſe of thoſe benefits wherwith herſelfe is fee'd, and vndermined, by the Paſſions. So that when our harts are once poſſeſt with any vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment affection, the <hi>Wit</hi> on the one ſide labours to find out rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons preſently, that may counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance &amp; grace it: and the <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination</hi> on the other ſide, like a deceitfull Counſellor, ſeeking to blinde the eyes of the Iudge, repreſents them to the <hi>Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing</hi> in a moſt intenſiue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and with more ſhowe and appearance then they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede. Neither can the <hi>Soule</hi> (which by reaſon of her limitted
<pb facs="tcp:19401:21"/>influence, cannot poſſibly at one &amp; the ſame inſtant, impart ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient actiuity to 2. differing ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations) exactly then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the ſoundneſſe of ſuch arguments, as might ſtay the violence of her courſe in folowing the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: but like a weaker Prince, ſuffers herſelfe (for quietnes ſake) to be led away by the ſuggeſtions of ſuch her followers. And hence it was that a certain <hi>Orator,</hi> with no ſmal aduantage to himſelf, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as he was to pleade, would moſt earneſtly entreate the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that he might be firſt heard, but ſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelf diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dnes of his cauſe. For he knew ful well, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had ended, their mindes would be ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19401:21"/>buſied in examining the weight and firmneſſe of his reaſons, that they could not poſſibly giue any diligent attention to the allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his aduerſary. Wherfore who-ſo-euer perceiueth thoſe proofes and inducements that ſhould maintaine his cauſe, to be wanting, let him ſettle himſelf to worke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the affections of ſuch as are to further it. For, if he gain neuer ſo little footing heere, hee need not deſpair of any thing. It was a ſaying of a prince of <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> that for a man to keep himſelf ſtrictly to the rule of <hi>Justice,</hi> in matters which concern'd his friends, was but a colour, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſuch as were vnwilling to doe for them, were content
<pb facs="tcp:19401:22"/>to ſhadowe their inhumanitie: and therefore writing to <hi>Idrien,</hi> Prince of <hi>Caria,</hi> for the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a certaine friend of his; <hi>If Nicias,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>haue not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, deliuer him; if hee haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, deliuer him for my ſake: but howſoeuer the matter goe, deliuer him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brutus</hi> &amp; <hi>Caſsius</hi> contending one againſt the other for the <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane Praetorſhip, Caeſar</hi> hauing heard their allegations, ſaid vnto his friends; It is true, that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which are alledged by <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> are moſt iuſt: but <hi>Brutus</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe muſt be preferd. So <hi>Brutus</hi> had the firſt place, and <hi>Caſsius</hi> the ſecond.</p>
               <p>Out of which exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples we may
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19401:22"/>eaſilie diſcerne, that <hi>Reaſon</hi> may giue out precepts, which <hi>Paſsion</hi> will not ſticke to countermaund. For, <hi>Reaſon</hi> teacheth vs, that it is a poynt of ciuilitie, to continue alwaies ſtedfaſt, and faithfull to our friends; but with this <hi>cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not beyond the Altar, that is, no further then the rules of pietie and equitie vvill giue vs leaue: which, blinder Paſſion dooth not a whit regard. And this, <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> knew ful wel, when beeing conſtrained one day to vnlodge ſomwhat in haſt, &amp; to leaue a certaine ſick friend of his, who as hee was readie to depart, beſought him that hee would not abandon and forſake him: <hi>O,</hi> quoth hee, returning
<pb facs="tcp:19401:23"/>back, <hi>how difficult a thing is it, to loue, &amp; to be wiſe, &amp; both at once!</hi> Beſides, it is the nature, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of <hi>Paſſions,</hi> euen to make thoſe thinges make with them, which (were not the eye of our <hi>Vnderſtanding</hi> dimm'd, &amp; obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, with ſuch miſtie humors as diſtill from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) would otherwiſe peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture proue to be as rubs and lets, which would turne the by as of mens conſent a cleane contrary way from our deſires: and therfore they are not much amiſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to a green glaſſe, which makes euery thing ſeeme of the ſame colour, that is ſeene thorough it. That fore-alledged <hi>Sparta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> being very much impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tun'd by his wife, to make her
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19401:23"/>brother <hi>Lyſander,</hi> his Admirall for the ſeas, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he had many Nobles of far more yeres, &amp; greater expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience then he; and that to inveſt him (beeing but a youth) with a charge ſo farre ſurmounting his ſufficiencie, was to hazard at one caſt, the flouriſhing eſtate of his whole kingdom: but in the end, after many long ſuſpenſions, and irreſolute determinations, the veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t affection which he bore his <hi>Queene,</hi> commanded him to throw the dice, and to abide the chance. It is ſaide of <hi>Agrippina,</hi> that ſhee did ſo worke vpon the loue which <hi>Claudius</hi> bore her, that <hi>nondum vxor potentiâ vx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oriâ vtebatur,</hi> beeing as yet
<pb facs="tcp:19401:24"/>but onely affianced vnto him, ſhe tooke vpon her the ſtate and power of an Empereſſe: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe was thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie aſſured of her marriage, and that her thoughts had got a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger wing to ſoare withall, then did ſhee dare to motion a match between <hi>Octauia, Caeſars</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and her owne ſonne <hi>Domiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> which (becauſe her father had betroathed her to <hi>Silanus</hi> not long before) coulde not bee brought to paſſe without impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: but that did nothing diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage her. For, <hi>nihil arduum vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tacitus</hi>) <hi>in animo principis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 12. 240. <hi>et</hi> 267.</note> 
                  <hi>cui non iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, non odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um inerat, niſi indita, et iuſſa:</hi> no difficultie could hinder her from
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19401:24"/>obtaining any thing at the hands of a Prince, that had ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life, nor ſoule, but what was breathed into him by her and hers.</p>
               <p>And hence it was, that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> vayling his ſeruile flatteries vnder the name of <hi>Cenſor,</hi> was embold'ned to faſten vpon <hi>Sila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> labouring by forged accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to obſcure his merit, and procure his ouerthrowe, which ſhortly after hee effected: <hi>Caeſar</hi> beeing (as our Author ſaith) <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiendis aduerſum generum ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionibus caritate filiae promptior;</hi> ſomwhat prone to entertain ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicions againſt his ſonne in law, by reaſon of the charitable af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which he bore his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
<pb facs="tcp:19401:25"/>And indeede the malignant aſpect of any perſon in authority towards his inferiour, is thought a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t warrant for euery man to wrong him. And this is the reaſon, that in the courts of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, few or none, after they once begin to ſlide, can recouer their footing, &amp; keep themſelues from falling finally. For, thoſe Court-Paraſites, that haue their eyes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually fixed vppon the sky of their Soueraignes inclination, &amp; make the ſundry revolutions of his affections, the only heauen of their conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plation, do labor vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the leaſt diſtaſt that is offred, to procure an vtter diſlike; that ſo they may come to be ſharers in thoſe offices &amp; places of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19401:25"/>which while they were gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the ſight of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, were appropriated to none but them: verifying heerby that excellent ſaying of the Greekes; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: when the tree begins once to fal, euery one haſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to gather ſticks. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore let no man feare to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bold in this caſe, but reſt vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly aſſured, that where <hi>Reaſon</hi> cannot preuaile, <hi>Affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> wil. And therefore it is not without cauſe, that ſuch as aſpire to a crown, &amp; ſcepter, do firſt of al (conſidering their want of right, that ſhould authorize, and make lawful ſuch a claime) endeuour (as the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie meanes to vvinde themſelues into the hearts of the people)
<pb facs="tcp:19401:26"/>to ſeem religious, and vertuous; as <hi>Pepin</hi> did, who ſtryuing to put the houſe of <hi>Merouée</hi> from the throne of <hi>France,</hi> and to appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate it wholly to him and his, did moſt infinitely honour, and moſt affectionatly imbrace, ſuch as had any charge or office in the Church; knowing wel, that thoſe which haue rule ouer the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, are of great authoritie, and eſtimation among the reſt. Secondly, they doe labor to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all offices of <hi>Loue,</hi> that may ſerue to ſhaddowe foorth in ſome apparant manner, a deſire in them to further the publique good of the State and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale. And thus did <hi>Abſalom,</hi> when to euery one that came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19401:26"/>him, he put out his hand, and tooke him &amp; kiſſed him: wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing withall, that he were once made Iudge in the Land, that ſuch as had any ſuits, or contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, might come to him, that he might doe them <hi>Iustice.</hi> And thus likewiſe did thoſe ancient Romane Captaines, who pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out the wealthy treaſures of whole kingdoms in exceſſiue donatiues, and prodigalities to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Souldiors; and that with no better intent, then to make ſure ſuch hopes &amp; expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, as <hi>Ambition</hi> long before had nouriſhed in their breaſtes, by the ſo-wonne ayde, and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of their militarie &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Legions.</hi> For indeede theſe
<pb facs="tcp:19401:27"/>two actions are the only harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that muſt lodge <hi>Perſwaſion</hi> in the boſome of a multitude. And therefore haue they alwaies been put in practiſe by the chiefe patron of wicked <hi>Policies,</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, the common and profeſſed enemy of mankind. For, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the firſt, the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth aſſure vs, that he doth often times, the better to deceiue, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe into the glorious ſimilitude of an <hi>Angel</hi> of light: &amp; hence was it, that not without good advice, and iudgement of the Paynter, in ſome ancient im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the <hi>Teſtament,</hi> hee was pictur'd out in the religious garment of a <hi>Monke;</hi> not to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie that the life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19401:27"/>of ſuch <hi>Monasticall perſons,</hi> was diabolicall; but to ſhewe, that this beeing the habit of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and pietie, there was not a more eaſie and certaine way for him to ſurpryze the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of wel-meaning men, then it. And as concerning the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, experience hath taught vs, that al he aymes at, is to work an impreſſion in our weaker minds, that whatſoeuer he ſeeketh to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce vs to, is for the good, and benefit of mankinde: &amp; therfore in his very firſt aſſault, wherein was ſucceſſiuely included the vtter ruine and ouerthrow of vs all, he told our firſt parents, that Gods forbidding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eate of the tree of good &amp; euil, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:19401:28"/>not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an enuious fear he had of that happineſſe and proſperity, which was like to redound to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: and withall, hauing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with himſelfe, that all thinges in the world, are ſaid in ſom ſort to ſeeke the higheſt, &amp; to couet more or leſſe the participation of GOD himſelfe; but eſpecially man, whom hee knew did foſter in his breaſt theſe three deſires; the one to liue alwaies, as GOD is eternall: the other, to rule all, as GOD is Lorde ouer all: the third, to knowe all, as GOD is wiſe aboue all: hee came like a cunning <hi>Rhetorician,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, and long experience, hath taught how to aduantage him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19401:28"/>by working vpon the knowne inclinations, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Auditory, &amp; layes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them a ful and perfect ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in euery one. For, ſaith he, if once yee but taſte of this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, <hi>nequaqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moriemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> ye ſhal neuer die; heere was a continued beeing: <hi>ſed eritis ſicut Dij,</hi> but yee ſhall be like Gods; heer was an abſolute co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund: <hi>ſcientes bonum, et malum,</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding both good and euill; and heerein was comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a vniuerſall, and boundleſſe knowledge.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, he that can handle men aright in their affections, &amp; knowes at what times, in what manner, and by what meanes
<pb facs="tcp:19401:29"/>they may beſt be ſtirred vp, may reſt aſſured, that before his mind be thoroughly knowne, he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie Maiſter of what his heart deſireth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the force of Reaſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE third, and laſt meanes to ground beliefe in the minds of men, is out of probable coniectures to gather ſufficient reaſons, by force wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we may demonſtrat the thing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19401:29"/>which wee propound, to be ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actually, or at leaſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly neceſſary, &amp; convenient, and no waies repugnant to the rules and principles of iuſtice, or honeſtie. And theſe are ſo much availeable, that where there is neyther opinion, nor affection, but rather an obſtinate, and ſelfe-will'd reſolution in the hearer, to put backe all perſwaſions, they will enforce him notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to alter his ſo-decreed deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and to giue credit &amp; approbation to what he heares. Witnes <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who when he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that <hi>Cicero</hi> had taken vpon him to defende <hi>Ligarius,</hi> whom the vnhappineſſe of the times had accus'd to haue borne
<pb facs="tcp:19401:30"/>armes againſt him, and hauing not heard him of a long time before; What will it now annoy vs, ſaid hee (by way of ieſting) to certaine of his friends, if we goe and liſten awhile to <hi>Cicero;</hi> for, as for <hi>Ligarius,</hi> he is by me already irrevocably condemn'd? But the pregnant reaſons, and forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble allegations of the <hi>Orator,</hi> did ſo wonderfully mooue him, that before he departed, mauger that prejudicat opinion where-with he came, hee was conſtrained to abſolue him.</p>
               <p>And for a further confirmation heereof, I will produce that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable apothegme of <hi>Thucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dides,</hi> who when <hi>Archidamus</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of him, which was the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19401:30"/>better wraſtler of him, or <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> his aunſwere was, that when he had caſt him, he had ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a tongue to deny it, that he made the ſtanders by belieue he was not foyl'd, and perſwaded them the contrary of what their eyes had ſeene.</p>
               <p>So that heere we may diſcouer an incongruitie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted by <hi>M. Brutus,</hi> in the managing of <hi>State affaires;</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not conſidering the force of <hi>Eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> but preſuming vpon the good opinion his Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens had of him, &amp; the great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they bore towards him, he permitted <hi>Anthony</hi> to performe the exequies of <hi>Caeſar</hi> in ſuch ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn maner as he would himſelf. For, by this meanes, the hearts
<pb facs="tcp:19401:31"/>of ſuch as were ſo deſperatlie bent, &amp; inclyn'd to embrace his faction, that they would not at the firſt ſo much as lende an eare, no not vpon his entreaties, to the ſpeeches of the other; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hearing of his ſunerall <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> were on a ſuddaine vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently carried a cleane contrary way. Such is the force of theſe <hi>Rhetoricall Enthymems,</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions; eſpecially, when they be ſeconded by a liuely and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent action: to which, <hi>Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> did attribute ſo much, that in deſyning an Oration, hee ſayd, the firſt &amp; principall part therof, was action; the ſecond, the ſame; and the third, no other. For, in an Orator, there is both an <hi>elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19401:31"/>of ſpeech, and a decencie of action neceſſarily required. He muſt not onely <hi>ornatè dicere, ſed etiam concinnè agere:</hi> the one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſts in the fitnes of his words, and ſoundnes of his reaſons; the other, in the variation of his voyce, and qualification of his geſtures. So that when I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in how eminent a degree theſe two things did appeare in <hi>Cicero,</hi> I cannot ſo much admire (as otherwiſe I ſhould) that nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpeech of his, when beeing vehemently diſpleaſed with <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once his eloquence had patroniz'd in a moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous cauſe) for that he did eger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie follow the extreamitie of law againſt a certaine friende of his,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:32"/>hee could not refraine from tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, that it was not long of his innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie that he was laſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, but of the duſt, which hee had caſt into the eyes of his Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which hind'red them from diſcerning aright the qualitie of his miſdeede. <hi>Aeſchines</hi> after his baniſhment beeing arryu'd at <hi>Rhodes,</hi> in an Oration compoſed for the purpoſe, laid open to the people the cauſe of his exile: who wondering thervpon at the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that had baniſht him ſo vndeſeruedly; <hi>O</hi> (quoth hee) <hi>ye did not hear the forcible reaſons by which Demoſthenes cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mine:</hi> aſcribing whollie the cauſe of his misfortune, to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his aduerſary. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19401:32"/>he did not greatly erre, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared <hi>Rhetorick</hi> in an ill cauſe, to a dangerous weapon in a mad mans hand. It is an inſtrument which was at firſt inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for the eaſier managing of an vnruly populace, &amp; which is neuer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploid in his right kind, but in the weake &amp; crazie languiſhment of <hi>Eſtates.</hi> And indeed, if we do well conſider, we ſhal find that it hath moſt flouriſhed, where quietnes of gouernment hath been moſt impoveriſhed, as in thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealthes, where eyther the people, or the ignorant, or all, haue borne all the ſway; as namelie, that of <hi>Athens,</hi> of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> where al things did continuallie labour of a
<pb facs="tcp:19401:33"/>dangerous <hi>Epilepſie.</hi> For, in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſtabliſhed Gouernments, as thoſe of <hi>Sparta,</hi> and of <hi>Crete,</hi> it was neuer had in any great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, or eſtimation. Nay, they would haue whipt him out of their dominions, that ſhold haue made profeſſion of ſuch a lying and deceitfull Art.</p>
               <p>But it is not my purpoſe, for the abuſe of any thing, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the vſe of it: I will onely heerevpon aduertiſe him, that goeth about by <hi>Reaſons</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>Perſwaſion,</hi> to imitate heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the practice of wiſe <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> who apply the ſame Medicines to the ſame Maladies; but with particular reſpect, &amp; conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the conſtitution of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19401:33"/>Patient. For, the learned, and the ignorant, are not to be handled both alike. Popular allegations they pryze not, and deeper de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations theſe pearce not. Wherefore, hee muſt labour to finde out a meane, by which hee may deliuer deepe reaſons per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuouſly, and plauſible perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſharply; that by the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the one, &amp; the acuteneſs of the other, he may yeeld a full and perfect ſatisfaction to them both. And for the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance heerof, I will refer him to a diligent ſurvey of ſuch <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picall</hi> heads, and Common-pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as are by Orators accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be the arcenalls, &amp; ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes of perſwaſiue prouiſion;
<pb facs="tcp:19401:34"/>from whence, as neede requires, they draw thoſe ſolide amplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, which lend a maieſtical, and glorious luſter to their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: for, beeing nakedly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer'd, the motion they produce is eyther weake, or none at all. So that where there is neyther opinion, nor affection to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe credit, wee muſt ſeriouſlie endeuour to find out reaſons, &amp; inductions that may ſerue the turne, and know, that it will bee no ſmall furtherance to our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, if either by the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of any viſible obiect, or by ſome preceding extraordinarie action, that carrieth engrauen in the very front of it, the honourd characters of loue &amp; loyalty: we
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19401:34"/>can ſtrengthen our own perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and worke an alteration in the hearers paſſion. An example of the former wee haue in <hi>Cato:</hi> who perceiuing that the <hi>Rom</hi> did neglect, &amp; contemne the forces of the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> becauſe they were ſomwhat remote, and far diſtant from them, whervpon ſom inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venience might happily haue redounded to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welth, ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly green figges, which at that inſtant were brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, wherby they conceived, that the country was not ſo far as they imagin'd: for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the figs would haue bin dried, or corrupted; &amp; thervpon altered their opinion, &amp; became more reſpectiue. Of the latter,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:35"/>in <hi>Seianus:</hi> who hauing very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digally ventur'd his owne ſafety for the preſeruing of <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and that in a moſt dangerous, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſtrous accident, where ſad <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction</hi> ſeem'd to haue enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged her throat, for the ſpeedier deuouring of them, got this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage thereby, that as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaith, <hi>quanquam exitioſa ſuaderet, vt non ſui anxius, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſide audieba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> when his ſo-dooing, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture was grounded vpon no better conſideration, then the minoritie of his ambitious pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. But (for a finall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion of this diſcourſe) let <hi>Delphidius</hi> aſſure himſelfe, that if reaſons, &amp; arguments bee altogether wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, it wil little availe him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19401:35"/>
                  <hi>Numerius;</hi> and afterwards, feeling himſelfe ſorely trauailed for want of proofes, &amp; witneſſes to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vince him, to cry out in the vehemencie of his diſtemper'd paſſion, <hi>Ecquis erit nocens, floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſime Caeſar, ſi negare ſufficiet?</hi> will any man bee found guiltie, when to deny the fault, may be ſufficient to abſolue him? For, <hi>Julian,</hi> out of the ſerener calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his more ſetled iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, will preſently reply: <hi>Ecquis erit innocens, ſi accuſare ſufficiet?</hi> will any man bee founde guiltleſſe, when to accuſe him, may be ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne him?</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:36"/>
            <head>Of Prayſes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE loue of <hi>Prayſe,</hi> though it be a vice, yet becauſe that by meanes of it, far greater vices are ſuppreſſed, hath alwaies (of the better ſort of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) been honoured, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected as a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue:</hi> the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt whereof, was made an argument to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vince <hi>Tiberius,</hi> of contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning likewiſe thoſe heroical and princely actions, whereby men
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19401:36"/>are ledde through many difficult &amp; dangerous paſſages, in a moſt eager and violent purſuit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Contemptu famae contemni vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tacit. Optimi. n. qui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mortalium altiſſima cupiunt.</hi> And indeed, if we but caſt an eye a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle on the <hi>Romans,</hi> we ſhall find that the onely thing which made men thinke, that ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie <hi>Genius</hi> did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually wait, &amp; attend vpon al their attempts, rayſing the valour of euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and individuall perſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, to a farre higher pitch, then humane weaknes was euer thought poſſible to attaine vnto, was only an vnſatiable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, to leaue behind them a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous remembrance of their
<pb facs="tcp:19401:37"/>name, from the effecting wherof, not death it ſelfe (had hee neuer ſo fearfully diſguis'd his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance) could euer haue deterr'd them. Witneſſe that vndaunted <hi>Curtius:</hi> who when the Oracle had commaunded ſome one to be caſt head-long into that open pit, which ſeem'd to threaten ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and deſolation to them all, as an attoneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that might alay the incenſed fury of the Gods to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the people; arm'd himſelf preſently, &amp; with ſuch a fearleſſe and conſtant reſolution, hied him to the place, as if vpon his very firſt approach he had inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to tryumph ouer <hi>Death,</hi> &amp; giue <hi>Deſtruction</hi> the ouerthrow. So <hi>Brutus,</hi> when for the good and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19401:37"/>preſeruation of his Country (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the liberty whereof, his ſons, as men wholly poſſeſt with diſlike, and diſcontentment at thinges preſent, did vnderhand oppoſe themſelues) hee was to be not only a Spectator, but an Actor likewiſe in their tragicke fall, could not chooſe but feele himſelfe ſorely ſhaken, with the furious &amp; violent incounters of divided <hi>Paſſions: Popular applauſe</hi> diſtracting him on the one ſide, and <hi>Fatherly affection</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But this in the end (like too weake an enemy to confront ſo great an adverſary) was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to forſake the fielde, and to reſigne the honour and glorie of the victorie to vs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:38"/>
            <q>
               <hi>Vicit amor patriae, laudíſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> immenſa cupido.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>But, not to ſtand vpon particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, the whole Nation in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall was ſo tranſported with this appetite of <hi>Praiſe,</hi> that all other irregularities whatſoeuer, did as it were lie buried in this one. Wherefore, (I thinke) there is no readier way to breede a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe in the minds of vnriper youth, whereby to make them ſeriouſlie addicted to embrace the harſher rudiments of <hi>Vertue,</hi> that afterwards they may attaine to a more eſſentiall knowledge in the managing, &amp; performance of honorable imploiments, then to enflame their tender boſoms with a deſire of <hi>Commendation;</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:19401:38"/>which is in euery generous, and ingenious diſpoſition, the onely ſpurre to any vertuous action. <hi>Compertum ego habeo</hi> (ſaide <hi>Cati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> to his ſouldiors) <hi>verba vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem non addere, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ex ignauo ſtrenuum, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> forte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex timido ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitum oratione Imperatoris fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</hi> No, no (ſaith hee) <hi>quemne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> gloria, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pericula excitant, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quicquam hortere.</hi> By vertue of which words, hee did inſpire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſuch a valiant reſolution, that after the vnfortunate euent of warre had bereft them of their General, it was wonderful to ſee the invincible courage, which had ſpred it ſelfe through euerie particular branch of his whole Armie. For, as <hi>Sallust</hi> wrytes, <hi>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19401:39"/>quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vivus pugnando locum ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat, eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amiſsâ animâ corpore te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gebat:</hi> looke what place euerie one had taken to fight in whilſt he was aliue, the ſame did he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with his body after hee was dead: leauing behinde them an example, wherevpon poſteritie might ground the memorable ſaying of that woorthy Martialiſt <hi>Conſalvo,</hi> who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Captaines adviſed him (by reaſon of the weaknes of his forces) to turne back to <hi>Capua,</hi> did vtterly repell their counſaile, as preiudiciall to the honour and reputation of a Souldior; telling them, if the true ſpirit of <hi>Magnanimitie</hi> had har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd in their boſoms, they wold haue deſired rather to haue
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19401:39"/>had their graues digged pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentlie a foote further, then by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyring, to haue prolongd their liues a hundred yeeres.</p>
            <p>The fore-alledged Hiſtorian, ſpeaking of the ancient flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eſtate of <hi>Rome,</hi> before ſuch time as the diſſolute exceſſe, and effeminate nyceneſſe of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter age, had (like a Canker) ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into the very marrow of her, and through a vicious in-bred habit and diſpoſition, alt'red the ſweete complexion of her coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, ranks this deſire of prayſe amongſt the chiefeſt cauſes of her tranſcendent hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. Her Children (ſaith hee) were <hi>laudis auidi,</hi> full of thrift in husbanding their honor;
<pb facs="tcp:19401:40"/>but <hi>pecuniae liberales,</hi> very prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall in ſpending of their wealth: <hi>gloriae maximum certamen inter ipſos erat;</hi> Glory was the onelie ſubiect of all their differences &amp; contentions.
<note place="margin">Laudatas of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendit avu Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonia pennas: Si tacitus ſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, illa recondit opes.</note> 
               <hi>Sic ſe quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hostem ferire, murum aſcendere, conſpici, dum tale facinus faceret, propera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat:</hi> which I cannot thinke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſo much from vanitie, as from a deſire to publiſh &amp; make known their ſufficiencie, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards for the good of their Country, they might be call'd to offices of a higher nature.</p>
            <p>A certaine <hi>Laconien</hi> at the feaſt of <hi>Olympike</hi>-games, beeing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred a great ſum of mony, not to preſent himſelfe to combat, would by no meanes be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19401:40"/>to accept it. And in the end, beeing demaunded of one, what the praiſe which with ſuch labor, and ſweat he had purchaſt, could auaile him; his aunſwere was in ſmyling manner, that he ſhould fight for it in battaile before the King. <hi>Eò labor, et periculum à ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſque impe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditur, vnde bonos, et e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molumentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſperatur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Liuie.</hi> And indeede, if wee ſuffer our Senſes to be guided a little by <hi>Obſeruation,</hi> we ſhall eaſilie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that in thoſe Camps, where Prayſe and Honour haue been ioyn'd patent with Exerciſe, for the training vp of youth in arms, there hath not been a priuat ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, but when occaſion hath brought him on the ſcene to bide
<pb facs="tcp:19401:41"/>ſome tryall of his proficiencie, hath beene thought woorthy, by reaſon of his Martiall carriage and aſpect, to haue the leading, &amp; conducting of an army. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the <hi>Ottomans:</hi> who by taking notice of euery extraordinarie action, performed by the leaſt, &amp; meaneſt in their troopes, haue ſo enflamed the courage of their <hi>Muſulmans,</hi> that now the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a Trumpet amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is but to foretell the erecting of a Trophie; &amp; the ſtriking vp of a Drumme, is as a paſſing-bell to giue warning, of the approching ruine and ſubverſion of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>And, by this meanes haue they marcht (like tryumphant Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19401:41"/>ouer the bellies of the moſt victorious Nations; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king (as they paſſe along) the wretched carkaſes of ſlaughte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Chriſtians, litter for their ambitious and aſpyring pride to trample on. <hi>Peuertie,</hi> with them is not made an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and puſillanimitie, nor thought a let or impediment, to hinder <hi>Deſert</hi> from any place of eminencie. It is no principle in their Philoſophie, to meaſure Vertue by the ell of Fortune, or to reſpect her the leſſe, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bin trayn'd vp in a homelie cottage. No, the greateſt among them, will think it no detraction fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their reputation, to com, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or wherſoeuer, the <hi>ſtarre of merit</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19401:42"/>ſhal appear within the compaſſe of their <hi>Hemiſphere,</hi> &amp; offer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents of great value to her deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deere Infants, lay they in a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And heerein may their practice ſerue like a ſeuerer <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> to condemne vs of high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt her glorious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Maieſtie; and ſummoning the blood into our faces, make vs aſhamed of our erroneous, and ſenſeleſſe follie, <hi>qui omnia prae diuitijs humana ſpernimus, nec honori magno locum, nec virtuti putamus eſſe, niſi effuſae affluant opes:</hi> that iudge of her greatnes by outward circumſtances; thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it a thing impoſſible, that ſuch a puiſſant, &amp; mighty Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, ſhould abaſe herſelfe ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19401:42"/>farre, as to vouchſafe to lodge within the incloſure of a ſmokie roofe, or vaile her glory vnder the thred-bare habit of miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and wretched Want. But for all this, the goodnes of ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, makes me not ſo farre delighted with thoſe barbarous, and helliſh infidels, as that I ſhold erect a Tabernacle, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to dwell in a continuall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of their vertuous diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in this kind: and therefore I will now paſſe them ouer, and come to other Conſiderations of more weight, and moment in this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt whereof is, <hi>whom</hi> we prayſe; the ſecond, <hi>to whom;</hi> the third, <hi>for what;</hi> the fourth and
<pb facs="tcp:19401:43"/>laſt, is the end <hi>Why.</hi> In the firſt, men are very likely to erre, by too eaſily granting out their commendatory <hi>Letters;</hi> making them the eſcorte and guide, to bring a man vpon ſome future hopes, into the loue, and fauour of a third. Heerin therfore ought euery one to be very circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpect: for, if the merit of the party, doe not in ſome ſort anſwer the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is made of him, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſo much out of the Wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters reputation.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendes, etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aspice; ne mox </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Incutiant aliena tibipeccata pudorem.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Polyperchon,</hi> hauing entertaind a fellow for the report <hi>Xenocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> gaue of him, and finding af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards by his actions, that hee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19401:43"/>did no way deſerue it, writ to him, that thence-forwarde hee ſhould be more diligent in exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the worth and value of a man, before hee did commend him. But, becauſe the hearts of men are to him onely knowne, who is the ſearcher of all hearts, and who alone could teſtifie of <hi>Nathanael</hi> with ſuch certainty as he did, that hee was an <hi>Jſraelite,</hi> in whom there was no guile, and that the rules of pietie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde vs to conceiue of their inward diſpoſition, by their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward converſation, that is, by coniectures of charity, and not by demonſtrations of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; our iudgements may be eaſily miſtaken in them:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:44"/>
            <q>
               <hi>Fallimur, et quondam non dignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tradimus.</hi>—</q>
            <p>And therefore the verſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may ſerue heere for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quem ſua culpa premet, deceptus omitte tueri.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>For he that takes vpon him the patronage of any man in this caſe, hee makes himſelfe an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the cryme. But for the better auoyding of all theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, it is good in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this nature, to make vſe of that reſtraint of <hi>Plato,</hi> who writing to <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant, in the behalfe of <hi>Helicon</hi> the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zicenien;</hi> &amp; fearing leaſt he ſhold attribute too much to his words, limited his beliefe with this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that what he writ, hee writ,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19401:44"/>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: of a creature, who by nature was the very obiect of change. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede man is a Tree, the fruite whereof is neuer rype but in the latter ſeaſon: his nature cannot eaſily be diſcerned while it is in greene: vve muſt ſee the floure, &amp; the fruit of it. His firſt actions lightly neuer iſſue forth, but ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with the beautious mask of formall diſſimulation: &amp; ſuch a one enters into the Popedom, as common rumor did report of <hi>Boniface,</hi> like a <hi>Fox,</hi> that raignes in it like a <hi>Lyon,</hi> and goes out of it like a <hi>Dogge. Il dì loda la ſera,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Italian;</hi> It is the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning muſt commend the day: &amp; the life of man muſt be cenſured
<pb facs="tcp:19401:45"/>by his end. There are ſom which now reſolue with themſelues to put on the grauitie of <hi>Cato;</hi> but preſently ſhow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, apparelled with the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute lightneſſe of <hi>Vatinius.</hi> One while <hi>Curius</hi> is not auſtere e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for them, <hi>Fabricius</hi> not poore inough, <hi>Tubero</hi> not ſparing and thrifty enough: yet by &amp; by they wil not ſtick to prouoke <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinius</hi> with their riches, <hi>Apicius</hi> with their riots, <hi>Mecaenas</hi> with their dainties: ſo great and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult a thing is it, <hi>vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> to meaſure out this earthlie courſe of ours, with one, and the ſame paſe. No: there are fewe in this corrupted age, that are not ſomwhat tainted with the humor
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19401:45"/>of that fantaſtical Muſician, who, as the Poet writes of him,
<q>
                  <l>— <hi>ſaepè velut qui</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Currebat fugiens hoſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſaepè velut qui</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iunonis ſacra ferret: habebat ſaepè ducentos,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saepè dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſervos; modò, reges, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tetrarchas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Omnia magna loquens: modò, ſit mihi menſa tripes, &amp;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cha ſalis puri, et toga, quae defendere frigus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quamvis craſſa queat:</hi> —</l>
               </q> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this his outward profeſsion of frugalitie,
<q>
                  <l>— <hi>decies cent ena dediſſes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Huic parco, paucis contento, quin<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> diebus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nilerat in loculis: noctes vigilabat ad ipſum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Manè: diem totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtertebat: nil fuit vnquam </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sic impar ſibi.</hi> —</l>
               </q> Yea, there is not one, of whom that may bee truly ſaide, which the Spirit of all truth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to be true in <hi>Helcana, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muels</hi> Father; who, for that hee ſuffered not himſelfe to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with any ſuch humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous fluctuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but remained co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually firme vpon his ſquare,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:46"/>and vnſhaken, was ſaide to be <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus vir,</hi> one and the ſelfe ſame man alwaies, what ſiniſter acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents ſoeuer did befall him. And therfore let not him that is care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of his credit, launch too farre out into the prayſes of any man, but keepe neere vnto the ſhore, &amp; on the lee-ſide of ſuch vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate euents as may any wayes endanger it: let him not be too forward in ſuperlatiues; but ſo commend good men, as hee may ſtill reſerue a <hi>caueat</hi> for their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
            <p>The ſecond conſideration that wee are to haue in matters of Praiſes, is, <hi>to whom.</hi> Many men (what by reaſon of the weaknes of their iudgements, ſomewhat
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19401:46"/>tainted with <hi>Selfe-conceit,</hi> or the greatneſſe of their <hi>Spirits,</hi> not principled peradventure with ſuch ſounde inſtructions as they ought to be) are ſo tender, and iealous of their own reputation, that whatſoeuer they hear attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the worth, and merit of another, is preſently taken by them, as derogated from their owne. And hence it is, that to commend a man for any ſpeciall vertue, or eminencie that is in him, either to his ſuperior, or his equall, is to make him oftentimes ſuſpected of the one, enuyed of the other, and himſelfe that doth it, hated of both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solyman</hi> the great, hauing heard the acclamations, and cryes of
<pb facs="tcp:19401:47"/>ioy, which by a generall conſent of the whole Campe, were giuen to <hi>Muſtapha</hi> his ſonne, at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from <hi>Perſia,</hi> grew ſo enrag'd thereat, that after hee had moſt ſauagely ſtrangled him in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner chamber, he cauſed his dead bodie to bee caſt out to the view of his whole Army: proclaiming withall, that as there was but one <hi>God</hi> in heauen; ſo was there but one <hi>Sultan</hi> vpon earth. Nor was the maſſacre of this his warlike ſonne the period of his furie. He likewiſe exerciſed this his inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and beaſtlie crueltie vpon <hi>Sultan Gobé,</hi> his ſecond Sonne, for bewayling onely the fatall and vntimely miſcarriage of his brother: and vpon <hi>Sultan Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemet,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:19401:47"/>his third, becauſe he fled for feare; conſtruing theſe their actions, by no better rules, then his owne diſordinate and crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall affections, to be moſt ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reproouers of that his bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, and vnnaturall inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: So little could he brooke a ſharer with him-ſelfe, in the glorie of his ſo great an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre.</p>
            <p>But (alas!) he is not the only man, that hath bin ſubiect to the commaunde of ſuch irregular, &amp; confuſed <hi>Paſſions.</hi> Many haue deſerued to bee parallell'd with him in the like kinde. For, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo-euer they made not ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a profeſſion of tyrannie as hee, but like cunning Paynters,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:48"/>could ſo ſhadow their malicious proceedings, as that they neuer came abroad in their owne like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but apparrell'd with the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward habit of <hi>Law</hi> &amp; <hi>Juſtice;</hi> yet can they not be altogether freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deepe-wounding ſtroke of ſuch deſerued imputations.</p>
            <p>I coulde inſtance the truth of this aſſertion vpon many: but, for breuitie ſake, I purpoſe to omit them, &amp; come to <hi>Tiberius;</hi> who, vnderſtanding that the Senate was minded to grace the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his Mother, with freſh additions of honourable titles, endeuors by wiſe pretexts to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their ſo decree'd determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: tells them they muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a moderation, in graunting
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19401:48"/>any ſpeciall preheminences, or prerogatiues to women: him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wold expreſſe the like tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perancie, in qualifying thoſe that ſhould be attributed to him. But, what-ſoeuer hee pretended in words, it is manifeſt, that this his outwardly profeſſed modeſtie, proceeded from no better grounde, then from an enuious diſtaſte he had of her aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And therefore (as <hi>Tacitus</hi> reports) he would not ſo much as aſſigne her one <hi>lictor, Mulie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre fastigiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in diminutione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſui ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiens:</hi> thinking with himſelfe, that vnleſſe hee topt the ſpred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding branches of her glory, they could not chooſe but fall out to be very hurtfull and preiudiciall,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:49"/>by their ouerſhaddowing great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to the proſperous &amp; flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing vpriſing of his owne. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> will at no hand admit of any more then one onely <hi>Sunne:</hi> and whoſoeuer ſhall preſume to parallel his atchiuements (were it with the valorous attempts of his Father) ſhall hardly free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from being made the tragick ſubiect of his ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed furie. Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces cannot brooke, that eyther their Vertues, or their Fortunes, ſhould admit compariſon. As they haue the ſtart of all men in the one: ſo loue they not to bee out-ſtript by any in the other. Such as are beneath the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in eſtate, and bounde by reaſon of their birth to acknowledge (as infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19401:49"/>homagers) a dependencie vpon their greatneſſe, muſt (in their preſence) eſteeme of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, how qualified ſoeuer, but euen as bare and naked <hi>Cyphers.</hi> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues alone will be thought the Numbers, that giue a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall exiſtence to the being of them all. <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> becauſe hee coulde not equall <hi>Philoxenus</hi> in Poetrie, nor <hi>Plato</hi> in diſcourſe, condemned the one to the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes, and ſent the other to bee ſolde for a ſlaue in the Iſland of <hi>Aegina.</hi> And hence was it, that <hi>Briſſon,</hi> running a match with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> was willing (inſtructed peradventure by the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples) ſomewhat to conceale, and obſcure his owne abilitie
<pb facs="tcp:19401:50"/>in the courſe: knowing (as it is indeed) that as to be permitted to contende in any thing with a Prince, is glorious; ſo to doe it with that obſtinacie, as not to giue ouer without victorie, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie dangerous. <hi>Favorinus</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Philoſopher, had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when his friends vpbraided him, for yielding himſelfe van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſht by <hi>Adria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> the Emperor, in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troverſie which was betwixt them, about the interpretation of a worde, to faſhion them this reply: What, ſaid he, would you that I ſhould ſeeme to bee more learned then hee who is Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder ouer thirtie legions? <hi>Augustus</hi> writ verſes againſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinius Pollio,</hi> &amp; I, ſaith <hi>Pollio,</hi> hold
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19401:50"/>my peace. It is no wiſedom for a man to ſhow himſelfe a <hi>Scribe</hi> againſt him, who (if he once be nere ſo little mooued) can eaſily proſcribe. And from this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, grew that witty ſaying of <hi>Carneades,</hi> that the children of Princes, neuer learnt any thing ſo well, as the managing of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. For, in all other exerciſes they tooke in hand, euery man was content to diſable himſelf to hearten them: but a horſe, that was neither Courtier, nor flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, threw the heyre apparant of a kingdome, with as little reſpect as he would the ſonne of a Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. Wherefore euery man (as well for his owne ſecuritie, as his friends ſafetie) muſt bee very
<pb facs="tcp:19401:51"/>nyce in commenting vppon his woorthineſſe, in the hearing of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſoueraigne authoritie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Regibus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Sallust) boni, quàm mali ſuſpectiores ſunt; ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> his aliena virtus formidolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa eſt.</hi> The goodneſſe of a ſubiect, giues Princes oftentimes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſuſpect; and his vertue doth but furniſh them with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of feare. Yea, the like reſpect muſt not be altogether neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in relating it, though but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their equalls, and ſuch, as in the neereſt degrees of conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity, may ſeeme allyed vnto him. For, ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times there is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger euen in thoſe: for proofe whereof, I wil produce one one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accident, which not long ſince
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19401:51"/>happened betweene two bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Ferrara.</hi> The one was the Cardinall <hi>Hippolitus da Este,</hi> who fell extreamely in loue with a neere kinſwoman of his owne: and perceiuing that ſhee with no leſſe affection doted likewiſe on <hi>Don Giulio,</hi> his naturall brother, whom very often, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him, out of the vehemencie of her <hi>Paſſion,</hi> ſhee would commende for the beſt-deſeruing gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that <hi>Italie</hi> then affoorded, extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling (among many other extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary parts wherwith Nature had ſufficiently inricht him both in body and mind) the beautie, and faireneſſe of his eyes, vvhich ſhee proteſted to the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, vvere the principall, and
<pb facs="tcp:19401:52"/>chiefe <hi>Solicitors</hi> of her affections towards him: Heereat he grew preſently ſo much enraged, that hauing waited his time, and opportunitie, one day as <hi>Giulio</hi> was a-hunting, moſt inhumane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie he depriued him of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both; glutting the viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie furie, with the ruinous defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of thoſe parts, which were the main diſturbers of his hopes: A tragedie fit to be recorded, as well in regarde of the perſon by whom it was acted, as in regarde of the thing that occaſioned the action. Which may ſerue vs like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for a precedent whereon to grounde this <hi>Caution;</hi> that it is not good to commend any man, ſo, as that the hearer may thinke
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19401:52"/>himſelfe any kinde of way diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled therby. And therfore, it will not be amiſſe for wiſer men, ſo to qualifie the approbation of their friends deſerts, as that they may not ſeem, either by their inward paſſion, or their outward words, to inſinuate an impoſſibilitie to the ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders-by, of euer matching their ſo eminent perfections, or to vpbraid them with a defectiue want of ſuch good parts, as they confidently giue out to bee ſo excellent in them: for this is but to expoſe himſelfe to danger, &amp; his friend to envie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>L. Quintius,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Cincin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus,</hi> when he tooke vpon him to plead for his ſonne <hi>Cęſo</hi> (who by carrying himſelfe as a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:19401:53"/>enemy to popular procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, had incurr'd the hatred, and diſpleaſure of the <hi>Tribunes,</hi> and thereby ſo endangered his life, as that nothing was left him but the very bare chance of the dyce to ſaue it) knew that to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage his worthineſſe, &amp; knowne deſeruing, as other his friends had done, was not the way to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him from their malice; but a meanes rather to ſet an edge vpon that envious diſlike, which ſo appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly threatned his vtter ouerthrowe. And therefore, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected (as it were) by a better diſcerning wiſdom then the reſt, hee chooſeth out a path (for the ſafetie of his Sonne) directlie contrarie to that which they had
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19401:53"/>trode: omits the recitall of his merites, as thinges not fitting to bee ſeene of a diſtempered ſight; acknowledgeth a faulte; and in that regarde, with great inſtancie, deſires the people (in humble and ſubmiſſiue tearmes) to beare with the weakeneſſe of his yeeres, and not to vrge the forfeiture of his vnadviſed er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
            <p>And indeede, it is farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome-times to confeſſe our ſelues tainted vvith ſuch impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, as (beeing vndeſerued<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie caſt vppon vs) cannot great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie blemiſh our reputation, then (by ſtanding obſtinatelie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon tearmes of innocencie) to contende with <hi>Greatneſſe;</hi> who
<pb facs="tcp:19401:54"/>would willingly enough (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) in colder bloode, admit a reconcilement, ſo it might not ſeeme to proceede from any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie or alteration of opinion in themſelues.</p>
            <p>The third conſideration is, <hi>for what. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnis fert omnia tellus:</hi> euery ground is not fit for euery ſeede; no more is euery man for euery action. The powerfull hand of irreprooueable wiſdom, hath divided our ſufficiencie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to little portions; ſo that he who is excellent in the leading of a Company, may happely prooue vnſufficient in the guiding and conducting of an Armie: which <hi>Saturninus</hi> did not ſticke to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance on himſelfe, when thoſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19401:54"/>which were his equalls in the warres, were minded to inveſt him with that abſolute co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand. Wherfore, whoſoeuer he be, that out of deſert (as it were) ſhall ſeeme to challenge a ſpeciall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of his own dexterity beyond all men, in the right per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of all things, hee doth but manifeſt his ouerweening weakneſſe in preſumptuous ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie; and what-ere hee be, that ſhall yeeld to him heerin, his vnwoorthy baſeneſſe in ſeruile flatterie.</p>
            <p>The heathen thought it a thing impoſſible, that any one Deitie ſhould be of power ſo infinite, as to be able of it ſelfe, to ſwaye the rule, and gouernment of this
<pb facs="tcp:19401:55"/>whole Vniuerſe: and therefore did they ſeeke out Gods of an inferiour nature, on whom (as vppon miniſtring Spirits) <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> the Superiour of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, might in ſome ſort vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthen him-ſelfe of ſo great a care; allotting to euery one of them (according to their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall endowments) a ſpeciall charge.</p>
            <p>And heer-hence it came, that one was ſurnamed ENYALIOS; another, MANTOOS; a third, KERDOOS; and that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> had her ſoueraignty allotted her in Nuptiall-chambers, rather then in Martiall-tents: as bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a thing altogether vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, that one of her compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19401:55"/>ſhould any way intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with Armes.</p>
            <p>But, that vvee may deſcend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine a little lower, to creatures of our ovvne moulde; doe wee not plainlie ſee, that in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of ſpirituall gifts, there is ſo great a difference, and varietie, that hee who hath the ſpirit of wiſedom, may want the vtterance of knowledge? he that hath fayth, may be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſtitute of the power to worke miracles? and hee that is endued with diuers tongues, may bee thoroughlie vnfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht of the meanes to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret them?</p>
            <p>The reaſon wherof, is deliuered
<pb facs="tcp:19401:56"/>by the mouth of <hi>Truth,</hi> in the 12. of the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> to be only this, viz. that there might bee amongſt vs a neceſſary vſe one of another; and that like ſo many ſeuerall members, wee might ſerue for the comforting, and building vp of one and the ſame bodie. <hi>Moſes,</hi> howſoeuer he excelled in all the learning of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> yet becauſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was not an <hi>Aaron,</hi> that could vtter things; nor a <hi>Iethro,</hi> that could order them in ſuch manner as was requiſite; hee was faine to craue the aſſiſtance of the one, and willingly follow the directions of the other. There is the like diuerſitie in the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch gifts as are vſuallie
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19401:56"/>tearmed naturall: ſo that he who is ſwifteſt in running, is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the nimbleſt in wreſtling. <hi>Castor gaudet equis; ovo progna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eodem, pugnis.</hi> Euery man hath his ſpeciall talent giuen him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue; and ought therefore to endeuor, as much as in him lyes, to beautifie, &amp; adorne that <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> which is befalne him. For, whoſoeuer ſhal attempt further, hee ſhall but manifeſt his weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and reape deſerued laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for his recompence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antony,</hi> angling one day in the preſence of <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> grewe diſcontent becauſe hee caught not any thing: but ſhe, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it, willed him (in ſmyling manner) to lay-by the lyne, as
<pb facs="tcp:19401:57"/>fitter for the <hi>Egyptians</hi> to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, then for him, whoſe handes were better taught how to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due whole Countries, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer Kingdoms, then how to manage ſo mean an inſtrument.</p>
            <p>Hence is it, that to giue out confidently of any man, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, that he is skilfull in many things, is but ſecretly to inſinuate, that hee is eminent in none. Mans iudgement and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie, is bounded with verie ſtrict limits. And it is a prouerbe no leſſe true then ancient, that he which grypes at moſt, doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies lightly faſten vppon leaſt. Wherfore, what-ere hee be, that deſires to advantage his friende by any commendations, let him
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19401:57"/>inſtance his ſpeeches alwaies on particulars: beſides, let him haue regard to the qualitie of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Philip,</hi> hearing his ſonne <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> ſing wonderfull well at a certaine banquet, wherevnto himſelfe was invited, did not ſtick to vpbraid him with his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie therein; asking him, if hee were not aſhamed to be ſo skilfull in a facultie, which was ſo farre belowe him: thinking, it ſhould ſeeme, that the following of ſuch things, as were no leſſe ful of vanity, then voyde of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, might argue a neglect of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable enterprizes; and ſo fal out to be preiudiciall to his the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growing reputation, rather then otherwiſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:58"/>
            <p>And indeede <hi>Prayſes</hi> are no way gracefull, vnleſſe they be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the troupe, and in the traine of ſuch as are proper vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. It is a kinde of ſcorne and indignitie, to pryze a man by ſuch abilities, as holde not ſome decent correſpondencie with his ranke; as likewiſe by ſuch as ought not to be the chiefe and principall in him. And this, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> knew full well: who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alwaies been a profeſſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie to the fore-ſaide <hi>Philip,</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> &amp; hearing that <hi>Aeſchines</hi> and <hi>Philocrates</hi> highlie commended him for that he was well-ſpoken, faire of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, &amp; could with eaſe ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low downe the largeſt cups, did
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19401:58"/>not ſticke to retort their ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches backe, to his diſgrace; tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, that none of all thoſe qualities, were any way beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the perſon of a prince. For, the one was rather the propertie of an <hi>Advocate;</hi> the other, of a <hi>Woman;</hi> &amp; the third, of a <hi>Sponge.</hi> So that prayſes, vnleſſe they be ſomwhat ſutable to the eſtate, &amp; condition of the partie who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee praiſe, they may prooue to be burthenſome vnto him, rather then otherwiſe; and therefore, due conſideration muſt be had of thoſe things, for which we goe about to commend ſuch as wee affect, before we doe apply the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; though of themſelues, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out extrinſecall relation, they be
<pb facs="tcp:19401:59"/>neuer ſo laudable. For, that which is a beautie in one face, (the right proportion of linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments well conſidered) may be a blemiſh in another.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the end <hi>Why.</hi> Mens acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons can not well be conſtrued by a better rule, then by the ſcope whereat they ayme. The firſt apparances of thinges are very dangerous, and deceitfull: and therefore, out of them it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to extract a ſetled iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their ſequel. The end a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is that, which muſt intitle them by the attribute of good, or euill. VVherefore, howſoeuer wee are bounde to giue our neighbours proceedings a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19401:59"/>interpretation; yet in thoſe thinges, which may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what neerelie concerne our ſelues, and vvherein wee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer not the drift of their deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, a wiſe diſtruſt, and ſlowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of beliefe, is not prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. They are the ſinewes of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: and whoſoeuer is ſo nyce and ſcrupulous, as to refuſe the benefit of them in this caſe, is no way to be pittied, if at length he reape the fruite of his ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous follie.</p>
            <p>Many there are, that haue hony in their mouthes, but wormwood in their hearts; and like vnto our <hi>Ower-men,</hi> looke one way, and row another: which, <hi>Alfonſo</hi> king
<pb facs="tcp:19401:60"/>of <hi>Naples,</hi> very wiſely diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a certaine Gentleman, that was a follower of his Court. For, hauing one day (with no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter intent, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make the ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſage for his calumnious detractions) exceedingly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto him the worth, &amp; good deſeruing of one, whom he hated euen vnto death; Surelie, ſaid the King to thoſe that were about him, this fellow goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to lay ſome ſnare wherein to entrap his enemy. And heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was hee nothing deceiued: for, ſhortly after (when by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his former commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hee thought his ſpeeches might paſs without ſuſpicion ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of enuie or malice) he came
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19401:60"/>vnto him with a contrary note. Wherefore, it behooues euerie man to ſtande warily vpon his guarde; as well for other mens good, as for his owne. <hi>Fronti nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la fides.</hi> Harpies haue Virgins faces, but Vultures talents: and the Hyaena, though it looke like a friend, deuoures like a foe. This world is a Theater, wherein no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is repreſented vnto vs, but in a perſonated faſhion. Looke into <hi>Epeus</hi> horſe; and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the outſide promiſe, you ſhall find in the bowels of it, the deſtruction of <hi>Troy.</hi> It may well argue a generous ſpirit, but with all, a want of iudgement in anie man, that on the ſuddaine ſhall repoſe much truſt, &amp; confidence
<pb facs="tcp:19401:61"/>in a reconciled friendſhip. The Lyon is a Lyon, though he ſhrink vp his clawes: &amp; there be many, who (notwithſtanding they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a ſincereneſſe of loue,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 13.</note> and affection, in all their dooings) want not a wil to conceiue a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, if they had means, &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to effect it. <hi>Tacitus,</hi> making a briefe recapitulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe cauſes, which brought <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gricola</hi> into diſgrace with <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> among others, rankes theſe kind of perſons, as the chiefe. <hi>Cauſa periculi,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>non crime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vllu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aut querela laeſi cuiuſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſed gloria viri; ac peſsimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inimicorum genus, laudantes.</hi> That which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered him, was not any crime in himſelfe, or complaint in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19401:61"/>but the greatneſſe of his worth; and (the moſt dangerous kinde of enemies) thoſe that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him. And indeed, in the courts of Tyrants (where, as <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> reports, <hi>honores pro crimine,</hi> honorable atchiuements are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted capitall offences; <hi>et ob virtutes certiſsimum exitium,</hi> and Vertue is rewarded but vvith ſure deſtruction) there needeth nothing to procure the downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall of a hated enemy, but a cunning applauding of his once ſuſpected merits.
<note place="margin">In vita Agric.</note> 
               <hi>Sinistra illic erga eminentes interpretatio; nec minus periculum ex magnâ fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ, quàm ex malâ.</hi> It is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thoſe inhumane <hi>Cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balls,</hi> to growe iealous of ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:19401:62"/>abilities as are reported to be ſo excellent in others; and wherof they find ſo great a want, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in themſelues. Their owne vicious diſpoſition, makes them apt, and prone enough to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the nature, and qualitie of mens deſires, by the greatnes of their deſerts.</p>
            <p>Hence was it that <hi>Tigellinus,</hi> a man renowmed vnder the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of <hi>Nero</hi> for diueliſh practices,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Annal. lib.</hi> 14.</note> that hee might with more eaſe, and leſſe ſuſpicion, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the ouerthrow both of <hi>Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> and <hi>Sylla,</hi> began (as our hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian ſaith) <hi>metum principis ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mari,</hi> to ſearch the feares, &amp; iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies of his Soueraigne: which after hee had once found out, he
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19401:62"/>did ſo cunningly worke vppon them, that with comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him their Nobilitie, together with their ſufficiency, he brought him ſhortly after, to be the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die actor of that vnhappy Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie, whereof himſelfe had bin the accurſed author. But Princes are not alwaies to be burthened with the diſaſtrous eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of ſuch proceedings. They doe but as weaker Patients, who by the counſaile, and adviſe of their Phyſician, doe ſwallowe often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a deadly poyſon, in ſtead of a wholſome drug: themſelues beeing altogether vnable to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the deceit, when arte and skill hath cunninglie diſguiſed it. In fenny regions, ſaith <hi>Varro,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Dere Ruſt.</hi> 15.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:19401:63"/>there are certain creatures bred, of quantitie ſo ſmall, that no eye can poſſibly diſcerne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; which beeing drawn with the very ayre thorough the noſtrils, into the braine, and through the mouth, into the body, are afterwards the cauſe of many da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. Thus, in the head of an <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian</hi> (as <hi>Holerius</hi> writes) was engendred a <hi>Scorpion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Praxis Medic:</hi>
               </note> &amp; that by his often ſmelling to the herbe <hi>Baſile.</hi> For euen ſo likewiſe may thoſe little <hi>Atomies</hi> be ſnuft vp with the ayre. No maruaile then if, with the prayſes of an ill-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected minde, there ſteale into the eares of Princes, that which may poyſon, and corrupt their iudgement, mouing their fancies
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19401:63"/>to a cauſeleſſe iealouſie of the partie prayſed.</p>
            <p>All men are prone to belieue thoſe things, that cary any ſhowe with them of ſecuring, either the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or their eſtates; as likewiſe to diſtruſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer a <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or a <hi>Guiſard,</hi> who neuer vnderſtoode the meaning of that worde <hi>Feare</hi> (out of the height of their vndaunted cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage) might in a careleſſe maner ſeeme to neglect the true relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of intended treacheries, or (ſcorning as it were a ſtrict en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie) confront them only with an invincible ſpirit, &amp; ſay, <hi>On n'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeroit,</hi> they dare not attempt it: yet where wiſdome is vs'd as an ingredient to qualify that, which
<pb facs="tcp:19401:64"/>exceedes in eyther, they may be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſoueraine preſeruatiues, and that without feare of preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to a generous and vertuous mind.</p>
            <p>But, that wee may not leeſe our ſelfes in things extrauagant, let vs draw ſome-what neerer to our home. There are another kinde of cunning vndermyners, who, when they ſee their aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, or ſuch as they affect not, advanced to any place of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the diſcharge whereof, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires an extraordinarie ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, will not let, as often as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is giuen, highly to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend their worth: but, if we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them, it is neuer lightlie,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19401:64"/>but with diſabling them in the maine. Thus hath <hi>Subtiltie</hi> been ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times the ſupplanter of true <hi>Deſert,</hi> and craftie <hi>Ignorance</hi> the depoſer and diſpoſſeſſer of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue.</hi> Thus was <hi>Taurion</hi> wrought out of the gouernment of <hi>Peloponneſus</hi> by <hi>Apelles,</hi> whilſt hee perſwaded the King that hee ſhould doe well, to employ ſuch worthy men as he, about his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: which conſideration, ſerv'd but as a colour to ſhadow his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter aimes; for, his direct and principall end, was to inveſt a creature of his owne with that charge and dignitie. Wherfore, it behooueth Princes, not to giue too much credit to the informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are giuen them by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:65"/>of ſuch as they imploy in any charges of importance; but for their owne ſafety, and theirs, to haue a certaine experimental knowledge, of themſelues.</p>
            <p>The Fencer ſome-times cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly takes his ayme at the foote, when his intent is to reach the head: and many men, by blaming the ſeruaunt, haue ſought the ouerthrowe of the Maiſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francis Sforza,</hi> being very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to remoue both <hi>Troilus</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter Brunorus,</hi> two Leaders of no ſmall account, from the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Alfonſo,</hi> king of <hi>Naples,</hi> framed a Letter, in the end wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee willed, that without delay they ſhould put in execution the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19401:65"/>conſultations that had paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them; which he conueyed in ſuch manner, as it fell into the handes of the king: who, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the contents, ſent them therevpon as priſoners into <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogne;</hi> and by that meanes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued himſelfe of the benefit, &amp; vſe of two experienced Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and gaue his enemy that contentment which hee looked for.</p>
            <p>I could inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the truth of this aſſertion on many more exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: but I am call'd away by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other kinde of ſiniſter prayſers, who are not abſolutely led with any malicious intent to offende others, but onely with a deſire to benefit themſelues; &amp; theſe are
<pb facs="tcp:19401:66"/>vſually termed flatterers. Their end is altogether different from the former: and howſoeuer they prooue to be no leſſe hurtfull the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of the reſt, yet is it but by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, and as the Ivie, corrupts the wall which it embraceth. But becauſe they are eaſily diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by purer iudgements, and ſuch as are not tainted with anie humorous <hi>Selfe-conceit,</hi> I will heare leaue both them &amp; this diſcourſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:19401:66"/>
            <head>Of Paines &amp; Induſtrie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter marke of a true generous diſpoſition, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt thoſe things, which are hard to bee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiued. The eaſineſſe of dooing, worketh oftentimes in ſome, an vtter diſtaſte of what is to bee done. <hi>Ingrata quae tuta:</hi> Vertue admits not facilitie for her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion; the path ſhee treads, it muſt be rough and thorny. No
<pb facs="tcp:19401:67"/>accidents haue power to make her turne her backe. Labour and paines, are the onely foode wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe fats herſelfe. The threats of Tyrants, tortures, and tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, are ſo farre from diſmaying her, that they ſerue rather to breathe a ſecond life into her.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Duris vt ilex tonſa bipennibus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nigrae feraci frondis in Algido,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Per damna, per caedes, ab ipſo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ducit opes, animum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ferro.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like a topt Elme, whom harder Axe bereaues</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Algid's</hi> fruitfull ſoyle of his blacke leaues,</l>
                  <l>Through loſs, through ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and exceſſiue paine,</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:19401:67"/>
                  <l>Euen from her wounds ſhe gathers ſtrength againe.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>It is no part of hers, to go cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping into a hollow Caue, or bee beholding to a maſſy toombe for freeing her from the ſtrokes of an incenſed fortune. She breaks not off her intended purpoſes, neither dooth ſhe alter her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded courſes, what-ſoeuer ſtorm, or te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt is like to happen.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si fractus illabatur orbis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Impavidam ferient ruinae.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though the wide world,</l>
                  <l>being broke, ſhould chance to fall,</l>
                  <l>Her may the ruines hurt,</l>
                  <l>but not appall.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>No: 't is in vulgar, and adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſpirits, that the ſoule of
<pb facs="tcp:19401:68"/>Motion is whollie deriued from the likelihood of Action. <hi>Avida eſt periculi Virtus:</hi> true noble diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, cannot reliſh any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize, further then it is ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with difficulties &amp; dangers. <hi>Edward</hi> the third of <hi>England,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding on what nice tearms the life of the Blacke-Prince, his ſonne, did ſtande, when at the towne of <hi>Crecy</hi> (by reaſon of the great advantage the <hi>French</hi> had of him, both in multitude of men, and commodiouſneſſe of place) he was (in all mens iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) accounted but as matter, out of whoſe ruines his enemies might frame vnto themſelues a glorious victorie: and fearing leaſt by ſending freſh ſupplies,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19401:68"/>he might hap to derogate from his tranſcending reputation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes him no better comfort, then this ſhort anſwere could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorde him; <hi>That eyther hee must win the fielde, or loſe his life: him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe would remaine a witneſſe of his valour, ready to ſecond what he had begun, when need required.</hi> This vnexpected meſſage, in ſo great a neceſſitie, from a father, was ſo far from diſmaying him, as that it rather added vigour to his ſtrength: ſo that, conſidering with himſelfe if he ouercame, his glory would be the more; if hee were ouercome, it could not be much leſſe; hee haſtens to the fielde, giues the onſet, &amp; enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles both the day, and place by
<pb facs="tcp:19401:69"/>the fall of thirtie thouſand of his adverſaries, 1500. of them bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Earles, Barons,</hi> and <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of note: which, like a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous feauer, did ſo ſhake eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie particular member of the Realme of <hi>France,</hi> as that long time after, it lay bed-rid of that ouerthrow. And indeed, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of conquering, yea, and ſome-times the feare of beeing conquer'd, hath to many Armies been the onely meanes, by which they haue obtained what they little ſought for. Witnes the firſt iuſt battaile, which the <hi>Romans</hi> fought againſt <hi>Hannibal,</hi> vnder the conduct of <hi>Sempronius</hi> the Conſull: in which, a troupe of well nigh tenne thouſand foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19401:69"/>were ſeiſed on the ſuddaine with ſuch an affright, that not ſeeing which way els they might make paſſage for their fainting baſeneſs, they caſt themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart one of the thickeſt ranks of their oppoſites, which they pearced with a wonderfull furie, to the great amazement, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfiture of the <hi>Carthaginians:</hi> but (alaſſe!) 't was but a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and diſhonourable flight, bought at the ſame pryce they might haue done a glorious and renowmed victorie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> made knowne vnto the vvorlde the ſingular proofe of his valour, vvhen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eing (with his Cohorts) to paſſe the Riuer <hi>Rubicon</hi> (which was
<pb facs="tcp:19401:70"/>the vtmoſt bound &amp; limit of his Prouince) and hauing weighed with himſelfe, the danger that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſo high an enterprize (wheras <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Safetie</hi> offred to kiſſe his feete vpon the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his proceedings) he ſets vp his reſt, throwes the dyce, and in a deſperate reſolution, cryes <hi>Haue at all:</hi> intending, it ſhould ſeeme (rather then hee would miſſe the purchaſe of his aymes) to poliſh and faſhion out his the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rough-hewen fortune, with the edge of his ſubduing ſword; and to make way for his ambitious hopes, through fieldes of Iron, and ſtreames of blood, to that imperiall dignitie, where-with in the end, hee ſaw himſelfe moſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19401:70"/>honourably poſſeſt.</p>
            <p>That Vertue is but weake, and ill deſerues the grace and credit of ſo high a ſtyle (being of it ſelfe vnable to giue life to any heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call deſſigne) that cannot with a fixed countenance out-ſtare the threatning eye of Danger, and make day for them, through all oppoſed diſcourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pelopidas,</hi> beeing advertiſed that <hi>Alexander</hi> came againſt him, with a farre greater Armie then his, was nothing mooued ther-with, but aunſwers preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: <hi>So much the better; wee ſhall ſubdue the more.</hi> The <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> were neuer wont to aske, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, how many are our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:71"/>but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, where be they: knowing their valour to be of ſo ſounde, and ſtrong a temper, as could not any way bee daunted with advantages. And this ſame warlike humour, which was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally bred in them, hath vpon vrgent neceſſitie beene found in many.</p>
            <p>It is an errour therefore, and an ouer-ſight (which in a skilfull Commander merits no excuſe) To depriue his enemies of all meanes &amp; opportunity of flight; enforcing them to exerciſe the ſtrength of their hands, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their owne baſenes would willinglie (perhaps) haue embraced any occaſion, that might haue put in vſe the ſwiftnes of their heeles.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:19401:71"/>
            <p>It was <hi>Scipios</hi> opinion; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iam hostibus, quâ fugiant, munienda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> For indeede, there is nothing ſo hard to bee withſtoode as armed <hi>Feare.</hi> Thoſe of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Lewis,</hi> Earle of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> vnwilling at all hands to receiue them againe into his fauour, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe with halters about their necks, they would aske pardon of him for their paſt offence; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled themſelues together to the number of 5. thouſand; went and confronted his Army of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſand; ouercame it, and free'd themſelues whollie from that Deſpotical kind of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to which before (vpon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different tearms) they offred to ſubmit both the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; theirs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:72"/>
            <p>The Earle of <hi>Fois,</hi> who in leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> three months (ſhewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Captaine, when hee was ſcarce a Souldier) had with ſuch valour, and celeritie, ennobled his name, by ſo many victories obtain'd in <hi>Italie,</hi> againſt the <hi>Spanyards,</hi> in the yeere 1512. was ſlaine by a troope of their <hi>Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,</hi> whilſt hee ſtroue to perfect his victorie; beeing not able to endure, that (all the reſt beeing ſcattered and diſcomfited) it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſhould depart the fielde as tryumphant, with her ranks vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broken, and vnſever'd.</p>
            <p>It is not good therefore for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man to preſume too much vpon his fortune. <hi>Vitrea eſt: tune cùm ſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>det, frangitur.</hi> And, as the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19401:72"/>French prouerbe dooth teſtifie, <hi>Par trop preſser l'anguille, on la perd:</hi> he that grypes an Eele too hard, is in danger to loſe it. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haue had the victory ſnatcht (as it were) out of their jawes, &amp; themſelues become the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable pryze of whome they had earſt moſt honourably ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryz'd, for not making a golden bridge for the retyring forces of their enemy to paſſe ouer: So great a power hath neceſſitie, to rowze vp the drowſie courages of men, and to enflame their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler livers, with a reſolution to ſel their liues at as high a rate as poſſibly they can, rather then of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelues <hi>gratìs,</hi> and vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged, to be like ſheep ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb facs="tcp:19401:73"/>by the furie of their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie. <hi>Vna ſalus victis, nulla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſalute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> What greater motiues or encouragements could haue been vſed, to ſupport the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a yielding Armie, then thoſe which <hi>Vectius</hi> applyed to his ſoldiers, when hee perceiued them to faint vnder the furious encounter of the <hi>Romans? What</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>are you deſirous to ſee your houſes, your wiues, your pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; your children? follow me. There are no walls, nor ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parts, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt your paſſage: Armes only are oppos'd to armes: your valour doth altogether equall theirs: but now neceſſitie giues you the vpper hand of them.</hi> And indeed, where haue we ſeen greater valiancie, then in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19401:73"/>thoſe deſperate troopes, that like <hi>Catilines</hi> ſedicious followers, <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitias, decus, gloriam, libertatem, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> patriam, in dextris portarunt;</hi> carried their wealth, their honor, their freedom, and their country in their hands. Witnes thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall inundations of warlike le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, which the populous fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of <hi>Scythia,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe colder clymats in former times haue afforded; who want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place to inhabit in at home, haue ſought abroad, &amp; by vertue of their ſwords, entitled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in moſt of the chiefeſt parts of Chriſtendom, diſſeiſing the right owners, and making themſelues <hi>Franc-tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> of their kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; poſſeſſions, both in <hi>law, and deed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:74"/>
            <p>The proofe heereof wee may ſee in the <hi>Longobards:</hi> who bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing driven (by want) to forſake their natiue ſoyle (which was an Iſland in the <hi>Alman-ſea,</hi> called <hi>Scandinavia</hi>) entred into <hi>Italie,</hi> made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues abſolute Lordes of <hi>Gallia Ciſalpina,</hi> and ſtyl'd it afterwards (in remembrance of their ſo wonne conqueſt) by the name of <hi>Lombardie:</hi> as likewiſe in the <hi>Huns,</hi> and <hi>Garians,</hi> who vnder the enſignes of that victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and ſo renowmed <hi>Attila,</hi> their king, after his expulſion out of the territories of <hi>France,</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed themſelues with the whole Country of <hi>Panonia,</hi> and by a compound name, called it <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia.</hi> And, that we may draw a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19401:74"/>little neerer to our owne home; the <hi>Normans</hi> (a people gathered together not onely from <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> but from <hi>Suedland,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Septentrionall</hi> Countries there adioyning) tooke ſuch ſure footing in <hi>Neustria</hi> (by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now <hi>Normandie</hi>) during the time that <hi>Charles,</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Groſse,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded it, that hee was faine, conſidering hee could not doe otherwiſe, to graunt it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally they would acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues euer after, <hi>liege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homagers</hi> for it to the Crowne of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue</hi> is neuer in her proper element, but when death &amp; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſeeme to haue hemm'd her in on euerie ſide: ſhee ſcornes the
<pb facs="tcp:19401:75"/>pryze, whoſe purchaſe requires not the vſe of all her nerues. <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peria dura tolle, quid virtus erit?</hi> ſaith the Tragick. <hi>Inveniet via<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aut faciet:</hi> Whereſoeuer ſhee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, ſhe will either find a way, or make one. No calamitie is of power ſufficient to bring her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. This Maieſty alone, knowes not what it is to ſuffer checke: it can neither be elevated, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. Her greatneſſe (like the higheſt heauens) is alwaies firme and without clowdes. Are you deſirous to ſee her? you ſhall finde her in the Temple, in the market, in the Court: you ſhall finde her ſtanding at a breache, or ſcaling of a wall; her garments duſtie, her countenaunce all
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19401:75"/>tann'd, and her hands as hard as Iron. VVherefore, whoſoeuer is poſſeſt with her, let him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelfe for dangerous aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Gladiator</hi> thinkes it a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, to ſee himſelfe compos'd with one, eyther in ſtrength, or skil, inferiour to himſelfe; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it is indeede) the victory cannot be glorious, which is not dangerous. <hi>Bellum cum captivis, &amp; foeminis, gerere non poſſum: Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matus ſit oportet, que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oderim,</hi> ſaid <hi>Alexander.</hi> And at the games of <hi>Olympus,</hi> hee vvould not runne, vnleſſe hee might haue Kings for his competitors in the purſuit of the victorie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul. Aemylius,</hi> by reaſon of the
<pb facs="tcp:19401:76"/>baſe, and fearefull ſpeeches, that iſſued out of the mouth of <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> after his captiuitie, thought himſelfe nothing honour'd by the ouerthrowe of ſo faint, and cowardlie a foe.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In Tauros ruunt Lybici Leones:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non ſunt Papilionibus molesti.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Againſt ſtout Bulls</l>
                  <l>the Lybian Lyons hie:</l>
                  <l>And ne're moleſt</l>
                  <l>the weaker Butterflie.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>The like doth <hi>Fortune; Fortiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos ſibi pares quaerit,</hi> ſhee lookes out the ſtrongeſt for hir <hi>Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists:</hi> the reſt ſhee paſſeth ouer with diſdaine.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tranſit tutos Fortuna ſinus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:19401:76"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Medio<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> rates quaerit in alto,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quarum feriunt ſuppara nubes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> Wherefore, whoſoeuer hee bee, whoſe happineſſe was neuer ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with any rough encounter, may reſt aſſur'd, that ſhe ſees no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in him able to ſuſtaine it; ſo that he need neuer feare her. His own baſenes doth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſecure him.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Servantur magnis isticervicibus vngues;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec gaudet tenui ſanguine tanta ſitis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> Shee ſeekes a <hi>Mutius,</hi> when ſhe is arm'd with fire: and glories in his vertue, that (like <hi>Fabricius</hi>) can ſhewe himſelfe an <hi>Atlas</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her vnder the heauy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of <hi>Pouerty:</hi> or that can with <hi>Rutilius,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>front her in the force
<pb facs="tcp:19401:77"/>of baniſhment: or with <hi>Regulus</hi> outſtare her in the horrible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of hell-bred tortures. Giue her a <hi>Socrates</hi> for her adverſarie, that can ſwallow poyſon with as vnchang'd a countenaunce, as hee would a delightfull potion: or a <hi>Cato,</hi> that dares challenge the field of Death, and hold him at hard play with his owne wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and then ſhe is pleaſd. An eaſie yielding ſpirit, ſhe eſteems a ſubiect too vnwoorthy for her ambition to worke vpon. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whoſoeuer ſhall at all times haue beene ſo pamperd vvith proſperitie, as that hee neuer felt the heauie hand of <hi>Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> let him not glorie in the mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſtarres, attributing
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19401:77"/>that peaceable, and calme tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie to the goodneſs of God towardes him; for this were but to flatter himſelfe in an errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous opinion. Let him rather take notice of his owne defects, and be aſſur'd, that hee is altogether deſtitute of that heroicall, and generous heat, that ſhould ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him to make head againſt <hi>Adverſitie,</hi> and is therefore pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſelie paſt ouer. Had he beene a <hi>Samſon,</hi> many thouſand <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listins</hi> ſhould haue bent the force of their malicious minds againſt him: or had hee beene a <hi>Dauid,</hi> a Lyon ſhould haue beene ſent to try him, and a Giant to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him.</p>
            <p>Did the all-ſeeing Eye of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:19401:78"/>diſcerne but the leaſt ſparke of vertue in any, he would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to lie buried vnder the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a ſecure, &amp; vncontroll'd eſtate: ſome ſtormy accident, or other, ſhould haue ſerv'd for winde to kindle it, and make it blaze foorth to the ſight of the whole world. Had not <hi>Rutilius</hi> bin wrongd, his innocencie had nere bin knowne. <hi>Illustrat for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna aliquos, dum vexat.</hi> Croſſe accidents are often-times the publiſhers of a concealed ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. <hi>Zeno</hi> knew himſelfe fitter for a Philoſopher, then a Merchant; yet ſeeing the life hee led was both pleaſant, and profitable, he was loth to giue it ouer, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the other: but hauing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19401:78"/>that the ſhips hee had at ſea, beeing very richly laden and vppon returne, were caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, he did then acknowledge a ſuperior prouidence; and out of a careleſſe apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſion (it ſhold ſeeme) of ſo great a loſſe, tells <hi>Fortune ſhee did well to range him to the gowne, and to the ſtudie of Philoſophie. Languet per inertiam ſaginata virtus.</hi> The edge of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie</hi> is cleane abated by the force of pleaſure, and ſecuritie. It is neuer buſied but when ſome vrgent inconvenience doth find it worke.</p>
            <p>After that man had forfeited thoſe faire poſſeſſions, in which his Lord, and Maker (out of the
<pb facs="tcp:19401:79"/>abundance of his fatherly loue) had placed him, &amp; was enforc't thereby with his poſteritie to ſhift for himſelfe in ſo vaſt, and deſolate a wilderneſſe, as the world was then; how quicklie ſundry arts Mechanicall, which otherwiſe perhaps had nere bin heard of, were found out, who can be ignorant? <hi>Want</hi> was their mother, howſoeuer <hi>Plenty</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards fell out to be their Nurſe. Yea, the like may bee likewiſe ſeene in creatures of an inferior nature: and hence is that of the <hi>Satyrist;</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quis expedivit Pſittaco ſuum</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Picaſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> docuit nostra verba conari?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where did the Parot learne</l>
                  <l>Good morrow Sir to cry,</l>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:19401:79"/>
                  <l>Or who the chattering Pyes did teach, </l>
                  <l>our words to proue &amp; try?</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>The reaſon whereof, is by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſet downe in the verſes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Magiſter artis, ingenî<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> largitor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venter, negatas artifex ſequi voces.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That which doth art impart,</l>
                  <l>and wit beſtow,</l>
                  <l>The belly, skill'd voyces</l>
                  <l>deny'd to know.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>This was it, that brought them to it, ſaith hee. But there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other reſpects ſufficient of themſelues, without the ayde of this, to worke the like effect in man: as, hope of gaine, feare of danger, &amp; ſuch like. Yet there be many of ſo effeminate, and ſoft a diſpoſition, that they are readie
<pb facs="tcp:19401:80"/>to ſwoune at the very firſt allaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any ſiniſter, and diſaſtrous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident: and whereas they ſhould employ themſelues in ſeeking to redreſſe what they cannot avoid, ſtande gazing one at another in the greateſt dangers, expecting ayde from the immortall Gods but not remembring, that (as the Grecian prouerb ſaith) they muſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, adde their owne induſtrie to th'invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of divine aſſiſtance; and not be followers of that <hi>Rustick</hi> in the <hi>Apologue,</hi> who, when his cart was layd faſt vp in the mire, ſtood ſtill, and lookt vpon it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring <hi>Hercules,</hi> by his celeſtiall power, to helpe him out with it: who beeing preſent, bad him put
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19401:80"/>his own hand to the wheele, prick forward his Oxen, and ſo cal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon GOD. For, as <hi>Cato</hi> ſaide in his aunſwere to <hi>Julius Caeſar, No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> votis, nec ſupplicijs muliebribus, deorum auxilia parantur.</hi> Gods helpe is not gotten onelie by wiſhes, prayers, and womaniſh ſupplications. It is by watching, by labouring, &amp; taking good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, that matters gaine a proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous and true ſucceſſe. <hi>Vbi ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, ignaviae te tradideris, nequicquam Deos implores: irati, infesti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſunt.</hi> If thou giue thy ſelf ouer to ſluggiſhnes and ſloth, in vaine dooeſt thou call vpon him: hee is diſpleaſed, and offended with thee. The clay, vnleſſe it be thoroughlie wrought, cannot
<pb facs="tcp:19401:81"/>poſſibly receiue the forme or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of a pot. <hi>Ceres,</hi> when ſhee ſhewed <hi>Triptolemus</hi> the vſe of Corne, ſhee gaue him this <hi>aviſo</hi> withall, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: vnleſſe thou cleanſe, and grind it, thou canſt neuer eate it. Inſinuating as it were thereby, that no man could poſſibly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any thing, to the purchaſe whereof he added not his owne induſtrie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour bore for an <hi>Impreſa</hi> the ſigne <hi>Capricorne,</hi> the conſtellation vnder which he was borne: and the word that gaue it life, was <hi>Fidem fati vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute ſequemur:</hi> Our vertue ſhall purſue that, which our fate hath promiſed; A <hi>Motto</hi> fitting the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19401:81"/>perſon of ſo noble and victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Prince. For, in euery acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is GOD that giues the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: but wee are they that muſt ſecond him in the giuing of it forme. Hee dooth nothing that concernes vs, without vs; no, not ſo much as ſaue vs. <hi>Dij labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus omnia vendunt.</hi> VVithout pains &amp; induſtry nothing can be got; &amp; with it, moſt things may:
<q>
                  <hi>Et labor ingeniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſeris dedit.</hi>—</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> had many imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which in an <hi>Orator</hi> were much vnſeemely: to redreſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therefore (ſaith <hi>Valerius) prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liatus est contra rerum naturam,</hi> hee made open warre againſt Nature, and vvent his way at length with triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phant conqueſt;
<pb facs="tcp:19401:82"/>hauing by the obſtinacie of his owne minde, maiſter'd the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignitie of hers: wherevppon it was rumour'd, that his Mother had brought forth one <hi>Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Industrie</hi> another. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though it be ſomwhat trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to take paines, yet once learne of a Mimik,
<q>
                  <hi>Feras quod laedit, vt quodprodeſt, perferas.</hi>
               </q> Beare that, which dooth a little diſpleaſe thee, that thou maiſt beare away that, which wil much profit thee. <hi>Fortiter malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur,</hi> ſaith the Comike, <hi>post po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Sowre accidents are ſeaſoned with ſweet events; and ſtormie tempeſts, are often fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with quiet calmes. And this was, though obſcurely, yet
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19401:82"/>moſt elegantly ſet out by <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> in that herbe <hi>Moly,</hi> to which he attributes a blacke roote, and a white flower; ſignifying the troubleſomneſſe of labor by the one, by which that tranquillitie of mind is obteyned, which is the reward of an abſolute vertue, expreſſed in the other.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:83"/>
            <head>Cautions in Friendſhip.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon, that <hi>Anacharſis</hi> when he ſlept, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes wont to hold his right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d on his mouth, and his left hand on his naturall parts; as if the one had needed a farre ſtronger reſtraint then the other. For there are many men of ſuch a temper, that they can with greater patience endure to carry burning coales in their
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19401:83"/>breaſts, then ſecrets: and hence is it, that thoſe thinges often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, which are whiſpered in the eare, are preſently after pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht in the Market.</p>
            <p>There are few, that can ſay, &amp; ſay truly, as that <hi>Graecian</hi> of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times did, who beeing told that his breath did ſmell, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it was by reaſon of the many ſecrets, which had a long time layne rotting, and putrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within him. Nay, many are neuer quiet, till they haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthened their boſomes of what they goe with (and that often-times without anie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, or choyce) vppon the firſt they happelie encounter, thogh the matter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne either
<pb facs="tcp:19401:84"/>themſelues, or their friends ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo neerely: but (alas!) in the end, they reape the fruit of their vnadviſed folly. It is an ancient ſaying, but very true;
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The good, or ill hap</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>in all a mans life,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Is the good, or ill choyce</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>of a friend, or a wife.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> Wherein, the cleereſt, &amp; beſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerning iudgements, may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie be deceiued. Many haue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in their mouthes, but a Razor at their girdle: and few doe vſe to carry a map of their mindes ingraven in their forheads. <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſimulationum involucris,</hi> ſaith the Orator, <hi>tegitur, et quaſivelis quibuſdam obtenditur vniuſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:19401:84"/>natura. Frons, oculi, vultus perſaepe mentiuntur; oratio ſaepiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè. Diſſimulation</hi> hath ſet her foote vpon the throat of <hi>Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie:</hi> and how-ſoeuer it be good, yet is it dangerous to meaſure others by our owne innocencie. The Marqueſs of <hi>Peſcara,</hi> was wont (as <hi>Guicciardine</hi> reports) to draw men into dangerous prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, and afterwards, by his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, and double dealing, to diſcouer them himſelfe; making other mens offences, the firſt ſtep to his owne greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>It was not mine enemie, ſaith the kinglie Prophet, that diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced mee, for then I could haue borne it: neither did he that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted mee, extoll himſelfe againſt
<pb facs="tcp:19401:85"/>mee; for then would I haue hid me from him: but thou; a man, whom I pryz'd as deerely as my ſelfe, my guide, and my familiar: who ſweetned our ſecrets by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting them together, and went in each others companie to the houſe of the Lord.</p>
            <p>As who ſhould ſay, 't was not my open enemy, nor my known adverſarie, that wronged me: but hee whoſe friendſhip I eſteem'd, not onely for worldly reſpects, but likewiſe for the zealous, and religious affection, which hee ſeem'd to nouriſh in his bowels towards the houſe of the Lord, 't was he, 't was he that deceiued me. Hence was it that <hi>Antigonus</hi> in his prayers, was wont to deſire
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19401:85"/>the Gods they would defende him againſt his friends. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demaunded, why not rather againſt his enemies: from them, ſaith he, that openly profeſſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilitie, I can eaſily beware; but from thoſe that vaile a wrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led hart, vnder a ſmiling counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, I ſtand in need of divine protection. And indeed, feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diftruſt ſecures vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of the one: but fearleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence betraies vs to the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries of the other. Who but our Sauior <hi>Chriſt</hi> could haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouered the ſecret practices of <hi>Judas?</hi> conſidering how forward he was to kiſſe him, &amp; likewiſe to performe all other ceremonious offices of loue that wer required.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:86"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ave</hi> is vttered often-times by ſome, who if their tongues ſhold not belye their harts, <hi>Cave</hi> wold ſound the trueſt in their mouths. <hi>Joab</hi> takes <hi>Amaſa</hi> by the bearde to kiſſe him, when he intends to kill him: and indeed, as the Poet witneſſeth;
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tuta, frequenſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> via est,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ouid. li.</hi> 1 <hi>de arte.</hi>
                        </note> 
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>per amici fallere nomen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It is a ſafe, and common way,</l>
                     <l>by friendſhip to deceiue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> And <hi>Socrates</hi> therevpon exclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Friendes, there is not any man a friende; meaning ſuch a one as the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick ſpeaketh of, <hi>Cui tuam rem cùm credideris, ſine omni curâ dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias:</hi> to whom, when thou haſt
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19401:86"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted any buſineſſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes thy ſelfe, thou need'ſt not interrupt thy owne ſleepe, with careful thinking on't. Some ſuch there are, but not in euery ſoyle: they muſt be ſought for amongſt liberall Arts; amongſt honeſt, &amp; vertuous offices; amongſt pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and induſtrious exerciſes: thy ſumptuous entertainement affoordes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not. <hi>Quae inter po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula contrahitur amicitia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca, vitrea eſt, &amp; fragilis.</hi> Cup-friendſhip, is of too brittle and glaſſie a ſubſtance to continue long.
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coena tibi, que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaparavit amicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, non te;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Martial. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigr.</hi> 15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eſſe putas fidae pectus amicitiae?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aprum amat, &amp; mullos, &amp; ſumen, &amp; ostrea,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tam benè ſi coenem, noster amicus eris.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19401:87"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whom plentious meales,</l>
                     <l>and tables make thy friend,</l>
                     <l>Think'ſt thou, his loue</l>
                     <l>can haue a truſty end?</l>
                     <l>He likes thy daintie cates;</l>
                     <l>hee likes not thee:</l>
                     <l>Make mee ſuch cheere,</l>
                     <l>and thou my friend ſhalt bee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> Theſe are like the <hi>Swallow,</hi> that changeth her habitation with the ſeaſon; and when comfort faileth her in one place, repaireth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to another: &amp; ſuch a one was <hi>Crottos</hi> mouſe; for while he was in proſperitie, it fed conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie with him: but his houſe beeing ſet on fire, it fled imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatlie from him. Wherevpon he tooke occaſion to frame this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtich,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19401:87"/>not ſo much to denote the vngratefulneſſe of ſo imperfect and baſe a creature, as the muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, and fleeting diſpoſition of trencher-amitie:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vixiſtimecum, Fortunâ matre; novercâ,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Me fugis: at poteras aequa, et iniqua pati.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou waſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to liue with me</l>
                     <l>while Fortune was a Mother:</l>
                     <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe a cruel ſtepdame grew,</l>
                     <l>thou left'ſt me for another:</l>
                     <l>But if ſo thou a creature vile,</l>
                     <l>and thankleſſe hadſt not bin,</l>
                     <l>Thou wold'ſt not haue deny'd to ſhare</l>
                     <l>the troubles I was in.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Hee therefore (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) dooth mainly erre, <hi>qui amicum in atrio quaerit, in convivio pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat;</hi> that ſeekes a friend in the
<pb facs="tcp:19401:88"/>Court, and without further try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, confirmes him in the Cup. It is a prepoſterous order, firſt to truſt, and afterwards to iudge: a methodicall proceeding, would require an inverted courſe. We are to deliberate of all thinges, with our friend; but firſt, of our friend himſelfe. There is no man ſo ſimple, but, before he intend to make vſe of a new veſſell, try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by the infuſion of water, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be well bound, and fit to containe more pretious liquour, or no. <hi>Alcibiades</hi> conveighed the image of a man into the darkeſt part of his houſe, and thither ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving brought his friends, one by one, tolde them hee had ſlaine a man, and withall defired, that by
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19401:88"/>their ayde, &amp; counſell, he might be ſo aſſiſted, as that the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther might be concealed: All of them deny to be partakers with him in ſo great a fact. Onely <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> willingly condeſcends to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his demaunds, by dooing him the beſt offices, which in that caſe he poſſibly could, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as yet altogether ignorant of the veritie of the thing: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon hee made no difficultie to embrace him euer after as his boſome-friend, and confidently to impart, vnto him, the vtmoſt, and inmoſt of his ſecrets: yet, in thoſe thinges by which his life might become queſtionable, he would not truſt his Mother, for feare ſhe might miſtake the black
<pb facs="tcp:19401:89"/>beane, for the white. Wherfore, euery man ought to be ſomwhat nyce and ſcrupulous in this kind; and not impart any thing, that may import eyther himſelfe, or his friend, but with ſufficient caution. For, as the <hi>Italian</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb witneſſeth:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Servo d'altrui ſi fà,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Chi dice il ſuo ſecreto, à chi no'l sà.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hee makes himſelfe a ſeruile</l>
                     <l>wretch to others euermore,</l>
                     <l>That tells his ſecrets vnto ſuch,</l>
                     <l>as knew them not before.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> Vnitie neuer paſſeth his bounds; but remaineth in it ſelfe alwaies one, &amp; is therefore called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: but the binary number is indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and the beginning of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19401:89"/>becauſe in doubling the vnitie, it turnes into pluralitie.</p>
            <p>A word, whilſt it remaines in him that firſt knew it, is ſecret: but when it comes to another, it beginnes to haue the name of a common report. And howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the <hi>Florentine</hi> be of opinion, that with one, any thing may bee ſpoken, becauſe the affirmation of the one, in caſe of detection, is no more availeable then the negation of the other (prouided alwaies he haue not ſuffred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be led by the perſwaſions of any, as <hi>Plautine</hi> was by <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> the Tribune, to commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie part of his minde to vvry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, vvhereby his owne hand, afterwardes may bee made the
<pb facs="tcp:19401:90"/>onely meanes to convince him; yet would I willingly giue no aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto him. For, howſoeuer it may ſeeme, for the faciliting of treacherous, and diſloyall prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, a neceſſarie <hi>Axiome,</hi> by force whereof, the lewd Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator being emboldned, dooth freely open himſelfe, to ſuch as hee is perſwaded may be eaſily drawn to ſecond his miſchieuous attempts; knowing, that if his expectation ſhould chaunce to faile him in any one, hee keepes himſelfe notwithſtanding out of the danger, and compaſſe of the law; whoſe <hi>Equitie</hi> pronounceth not the ſentence of death againſt any man, without a iuſt, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conviction, which in this caſe
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19401:90"/>(conſidering the many diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red paſſions, wherewith men are led to ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dalize each other) can not be had (witneſſe thoſe ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall duells, and combats, which heere-to-fore both in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and diuers others, haue beene aſſign'd by Princes for the avoyding of ſuch differences; the ſtaine of infamie and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, reſting alwaies, how iuſtly often-times God knowes, with the partie vanquiſhed, whither Plaintife, or Defendant): yet for the concealing of honeſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes, it is very hurtful, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. I call honeſt Counſailes, ſuch as concerne the publike good of my Prince, or the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate good of my friende; which
<pb facs="tcp:19401:91"/>indeed is ſo farre forth to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted good, as it ſtands with the good, or at leaſt not againſt the good of my ſupreame Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne; to whom, by a threefold law, to wit, Diuine, Naturall, &amp; Ciuill, I am bounde to purchaſe (with my beſt endeuours) all the good, and ſafetie, that I can. I owe all fayth, &amp; loyaltie to both; and am as a friende to ſatisfie with all alacritie the deſires of the one, ſo farre foorth as they impugne not the alleageance, which, as a ſubiect, I am to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the other.</p>
            <p>But, as I would not willinglie nouriſh a Serpent in my boſom, which in the end ſhould deuoure me: ſo on the other ſide, I would
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19401:91"/>not be too ſtrict and rigorous a Cenſurer of his deſſignes; leaſt by my raſh, and ſcandalous dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I brand both my ſelfe, and him, with an opprobrious mark of euerlaſting ignominy, &amp; that that of the Satyriſt may not bee truly ſaid of me;
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Stoïcus occidit Baream</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>delator amicum.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Hiſtories abounde with exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of this kinde: but the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull hande of heauen hath fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated the ambitious hopes of their effected villanie; &amp;, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they expected honour, and promotion, hath iuſtly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them vvith neuer-dying ſhame, and vtter confuſion. But becauſe a tragicall <hi>Catastrophe</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19401:92"/>to a friendlie diſcourſe, might ſeeme (peradventure) ſomwhat ominous, I will ſtretch the thred of my ſubiect to a further length.</p>
            <p>There are ſome that faſhion themſelues to nothing more, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how to become ſpeculatiue into another, to the end to know how to worke him, or winde him, or gouerne him: but this procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from a heart that is double, and cloven; and not entyre, and ingenuous. And as in frendſhip it argues a great defect, and want of integritie: ſo likewiſe towards ſome perſons, a defect of dutie: and ſuch as pleaſe themſelues in theſe barbarous ſpeculations, are to be no better accounted, then the very <hi>Gangrenes,</hi> and <hi>Canker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:19401:92"/>of humane ſocietie.
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Scire volunt ſecreta domus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> inde timeri.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They ſeeke the ſecrets</l>
                     <l>of our houſe to know,</l>
                     <l>That thence in vs</l>
                     <l>ſome feare of them might grow.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> And indeede, if they chance to come, where <hi>Diſsolution</hi> is the Steward of a diſord'red familie, their hopes flie right to their ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ayme; they gin to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd: but (alas!) that loue is but the ſpurious, &amp; adulterate iſſue of a conſcious &amp; guilty feare:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carus erit Verri, qui Verre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tempore quo vult</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Accuſare potest</hi> —</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To him no kindneſſe</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Verres</hi> will refuſe,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19401:93"/>
                     <l>That, when hee pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>can <hi>Verres</hi> life accuſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Hence was it, that <hi>Tigellinus</hi> (as our Hiſtorian witneſſeth) to adde the better ſtrength to his tranſcending fortune, endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (as much as in him lay) <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipem ſibi ſocietate ſceleru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere,</hi> to endeare the Prince vnto himſelfe, by making him a part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in his villanies: which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his brutiſh expectation he cunningly accompliſht. But, thoſe that like <hi>Ageſilaus,</hi> who in trauailing tooke vp his lodging alwaies in the Temples, to the intent that men, and Gods might ſee into his actions: or, like <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Druſus,</hi> who, when certaine Maſons had offred him for three
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19401:93"/>thouſand crowns, ſo to contriue his houſe, as that his neighbours ſhould no longer enioy that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen proſpect into it, which they had: I will giue you, ſaith he, fixe thouſand, and frame it ſo, that they may looke into it on euery ſide: thoſe, I ſay, that like theſe men, doe all things, <hi>tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet aliquis,</hi> as if they had a <hi>Cato</hi> in their boſome, that did continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie behold them, cannot eaſily be toucht, or tainted vvith the noyſome corruption of ſuch dangerous &amp; hurtfull flyes: nor likewiſe thoſe that ſhall but dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlie obſerue the difference, betweene a ſtarre, and a <hi>Meteor,</hi> a true friende, and a falſe: The one, is curious, and inquiſitiue
<pb facs="tcp:19401:94"/>to learne more then he ſhould; the other, is afraid to know more then he would: following there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>Philippides,</hi> who, when <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> demaunded of him, what of ſo many things that were his, hee ſhould communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate vnto him; Whatſoeuer it ſhal pleaſe you Sir, anſwered he, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſo it bee not of your ſecrets:</hi> diſtruſting it ſhould ſeeme his own imperfection, for the concealing them; or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it is indeed) <hi>arduu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nimis eſse meruiſse Principis ſecretum, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi ſi quid cognoſcitur, prodi velab alio formidatur.</hi> A prying eye, a liſtning eare, &amp; a prating tongue, are all birds of one wing; and by reaſon thereof, ſeldome times
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19401:94"/>found ſeparated one from an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For the better avoyding therefore of ſuch dangerous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, as the commerce and ſocietie of ſuch intemperate perſons might happelie bring with it, it would not be much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, ſecretlie to examine, what his carriage hath beene towards others his aſſociates in former times: and thereafter as we find it, to frame a ſetled reſolution in our ſelues; if faultie, abſolutelie to avoyde him: if otherwiſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently to embrace him. For to diſtruſt without a cauſe, is verie dangerous: I doe but teach an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to deceiue, by fearing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermuch my ſelfe to bee decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. This was it, which did anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilate
<pb facs="tcp:19401:95"/>the practices of peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, &amp; <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> king of <hi>France,</hi> in the yeere 1528. For, hauing (in a manner) accorded all their differences, the queſtion onely was, which of them both did beſt deſerue to be truſted. <hi>Caeſar</hi> gaue out he might not ſafely truſt him, that had once deceiued him: wherevnto, the <hi>Orators</hi> of <hi>France</hi> did witti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reply; that the more hee did pretende himſelfe to haue been deceiued by the King their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the more might the King their maiſter imagine he ſhould be deceiued by him.</p>
            <p>Hence was it that <hi>Otho,</hi> after the ouerthrow of <hi>Galba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tacit. hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto. lib.</hi> 1.</note> hauing deliuered <hi>Celſus, per ſpeciem vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culorum,</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:19401:95"/>vnder the colour of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer puniſhment, from the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his followers; <hi>non quaſi ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſceret,</hi> not by way of pardon (for hee would not ſeem to taxe him of any crime) but, leaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an enemie, <hi>metum reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis adhiberet,</hi> the ſincereneſs of his reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cilement might any way prooue queſtionable, hee rankt him preſently amongſt his dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt friends, &amp; made him withall, a ſpeciall Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mander in his after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wars: in which, hee behav'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as loyally, as euer hee had done in the imployments of his formerly depoſed Soueraigne. Vpon the good euent of which exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, <hi>Lew.</hi> 12. did peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rure ground that memorable anſwer,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:96"/>wherewith he nipt the bloody in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigations of thoſe Paraſits, that, after hee was come vnto the crowne, by the deceaſe of <hi>Charles</hi> the eight, did animate him to vengeance, againſt <hi>Lewis de la Trimouille,</hi> who during the raign of that aforeſaid Prince, had, in the battaile of Saint <hi>Aubin,</hi> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne his Armie, &amp; taken him. <hi>It is not fit</hi> (ſaid hee) <hi>a King of France ſhould marry the quarrels of a Duke of Orleans. If he ſerued faithfully the king his Maister a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me, who then was but Duke of Orleans; it is not to bee feared, but he will do the like for me hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward, who now am king of France.</hi> But where wee finde a defect of loyaltie in any towards
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19401:96"/>others, it is not ſafe to hazard our ſelues vpon the hope of their amendment towards vs.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— <hi>vetabo, qui Cereris ſacrum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgarit arcanae, ſub ijſdem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sit trabibus, fragilem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mecum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Solvat faſelum.</hi>—</l>
            </q>
            <p>It is true, that many are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to take the benefit, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of a treacherous ſubiect againſt his Maſter, in caſes of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility; but neuer loue to put him in truſt with any thing that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes themſelues: or if they do, it is with more then <hi>Juno's</hi> iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, or <hi>Argus</hi> obſeruation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, during the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene the <hi>Imperialls</hi> and the <hi>French,</hi> was willing to
<pb facs="tcp:19401:97"/>make what vſe hee could, of the diſloyall ſeruice of the D. of <hi>Bourbon</hi> againſt his Lord &amp; Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt: but howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he lov'd his actions, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer lik't his perſon. His infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie had purchaſt him the hatred, and diſlike of all men: for, after his arriuall to the Emperours Court, <hi>Caeſar</hi> hauing entertained him with all the friendly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, that were poſſible, ſent afterwards to deſire the houſe of one of his Nobles for to lodge him in: who anſwered the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger with a <hi>Castilian</hi> courage, <hi>That hee could not but ſatisfie his Maiesties demaunde: but let him knowe,</hi> ſaide hee, <hi>that Bourbon ſhall no ſooner bee gone out of it,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19401:97"/>but I will burne it; as beeing infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his infamie, and thereby made vnfit for men of honour to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vertue, and Vice are vtter op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites: and how-ſo-euer many ſeuerall accidents, and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may bring them to ſome complementall enterviewe, yet is it altogether impoſſible to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh a true, and perfit league of amitie betwixt them. There can bee no true fellowſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Light and Darknes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>Belial,</hi> Saint <hi>Michael</hi> and the <hi>Serpent.</hi> Where there is a difference therefore in <hi>Religion,</hi> there is alwaies lightly a diſcordancie in affection. And hence hath riſen that deadlie
<pb facs="tcp:19401:98"/>hatred betweene the <hi>Pagan,</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> and among <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> betweene the <hi>Catholick</hi> &amp; the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and the <hi>Puritan,</hi> the <hi>Puritan</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whilſt euery one contends to iuſtifie the ſoundneſſe, &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cereneſſe of his owne: but the Lord of heauen, the vnitie of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, vnite their harts, &amp; minds, together in the bonds of CHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RITIE, &amp; grant that the <hi>Church</hi> may not alwaies ſpeake in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded <hi>Dialect,</hi> to the diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of weaker <hi>Ignorance,</hi> who is not able (among ſo many divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded cryes) to diſtinguiſh the voyce of her lawfull <hi>Sheepheard.</hi> The Church of SARDIE giues out, that ſhe alone doth liue: and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19401:98"/>that of LAODICEA, that ſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone doth ſee, that ſhee alone is clothed: whereas, the <hi>Holy-one of holy ones</hi> pronounceth of the one, that ſhe is dead; and of the other, that ſhe is both blind, and naked.</p>
            <p>But, that I may not ſeem to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſweetneſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery flower, wandring too far from my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded courſe; there can be lightly no great affection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe that are of one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, whether it be <hi>liberall,</hi> or <hi>mechanicall. Figulus figulo,</hi> ſaith the Prouerb. There can bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Envie,</hi> and <hi>Emulation</hi> betweene thoſe that run at one, and the ſame goale, whatſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:19401:99"/>(whither <hi>Gaine,</hi> or <hi>Honour</hi>) be the proclaimed pryze of their contention. The one ſeeketh continually to ſupplant the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for his owne advantage.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hectora Priamide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> animosu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> inter Achille<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Irafuit capitalis, vt vltima diuideret mors:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non alia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ob cauſam, niſi quòd virtus in vtro<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Summa fuit.</hi>—</l>
               </q> So likewiſe, where there is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion eyther in meanes, or mindes, there can bee no other friendſhip, then that <hi>Microphilie,</hi> which <hi>Plato</hi> had with <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 13</note> 
               <hi>Quid enim communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabit olla ad cacabum?</hi> Wherein can the earthen Pipkin benefit the braſen Pot? Which conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the Emperour had reaſon, when worde was brought him,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19401:99"/>that a certaine Cardinall of the court of <hi>Rome,</hi> who before times had much affected him, was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced newlie to the Popedom, to ſay, that of a truſtie friend, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Cardinall, he would becom a deadly enemie beeing a Pope: and indeede, hee did prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate aright; for it fell out accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his expectation. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if thou would'ſt not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, take one, whoſe greatneſſe may not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awe thee: &amp; ſo when thou ſtand'ſt in need of his aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, thou ſhalt not feare that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortleſſe reply, which <hi>Abraham</hi> gaue to <hi>Diues</hi> in his torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; <hi>Nimis magnus eſt hia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus interte, et nos:</hi> ther is too great a diſtance betweene vs and thee.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:100"/>
            <p>Laſt of all, there can be no ſafe or ſetled converſation with him, who, as the Poet ſaith;
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>— <hi>abſentem rodit amicum:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aut non defendit alio culpante: ſolutos</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Qui captat riſus hominum, famam<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> dicacis:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fingere qui non viſapoteſt: commiſſa tacere</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Qui nequit</hi> —</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Gnawes, like a Cur,</l>
                     <l>vpon his abſent friend,</l>
                     <l>Or from <hi>Detraction</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>doth him not defend:</l>
                     <l>Affects profuſed laughter</l>
                     <l>at a feaſt,</l>
                     <l>And would be famous</l>
                     <l>for ſome byting ieſt:</l>
                     <l>Can faine the things,</l>
                     <l>which he did neuer ſee;</l>
                     <l>But not conceale ought</l>
                     <l>that he knowes, from thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:19401:100"/>
               <hi>Hic niger est</hi>—he carryes haye in his horne; and therefore —<hi>hunc tu Romane caveto:</hi> avoyde his company, if thou reſpect thine owne ſafetie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>Of three things prejudiciall to Secrecie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that hath made his boſome, <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſecretorum aerariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as it were the <hi>Storehouſe,</hi> or <hi>Eſchequer</hi> of his friendes ſecrets, muſt diligently take heede of
<pb facs="tcp:19401:101"/>three things, not ſuffering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in any caſe to be vanquiſht by any of them: and thoſe are, <hi>Wine, Women,</hi> and <hi>Anger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the firſt, <hi>Momus</hi> hauing taken a generall ſurvey of thoſe infinite deceits, which continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally were bred, &amp; foſtered in the hart of man, did moſt impiouſlie taxe his maker, &amp; Creator, of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion, in that hee made not ſome window open into his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, by which, the viſual beames of our externall <hi>Senſe,</hi> not mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with an impenetrable ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, might eaſily diſcouer what was done within: but wee, that know the workes of God to be euery way ſo abſolute, that, as the Poet ſaith,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19401:101"/>
               <q>
                  <l>— <hi>Non vllum carpere Livor</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Poſſit opus Domini</hi> —</l>
               </q> will with <hi>Plutarch</hi> aunſwere him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. lib.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>That we neede not the profane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of his fantasticall imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, to make knowne vnto vs, the darker minds, &amp; meanings one of another. Wine,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>doth in a most abundant manner diſcloſe our inward thoughts, and vnbare vs of that diſguis'd, and perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted habit, vnder the which we are accustomed to marche.</hi> The wiſer ſort of Princes therefore, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that verſe of <hi>Horace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Arte Poet.</note> are reported,
<q>
                  <l>— <hi>multis vrgere culullis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et torquere mero, quem perspexiſſe laborant,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>An fit amicitiâ dignus.</hi> —</l>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:19401:102"/>And indeed, the nature and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of man, dooth neuer lightly (as a certain Author wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily affirmes) open, and diſcouer it ſelfe at full, but either in <hi>oculis, loculis,</hi> or <hi>poculis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of the chiefeſt cauſes of the ouerthrowe of <hi>Claudius,</hi> was a word, which vnaduiſedly ſlipt from him in his drunkenneſſe; to wit, <hi>vt coniugum flagitia ferret, dein puniret:</hi> that for a while, he would beare with the intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancies of his wife, but in the end he would ſeuerely puniſh them: which, <hi>Agrippina</hi> fearing, as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall to herſelfe, went preſently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, for the better preuenting of her owne end, to haſten his. And indeed, <hi>Il vino, non ha ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone;</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:19401:102"/>wine, ſaith the Italian, hath no ſterne. Wherefore, hee that taſtes of it beyond the Cup of pleaſure, puts himſelfe in excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great danger of ſuffering ſhipwracke; conſidering hovv many are the envious <hi>Rocks,</hi> and vnſatiable <hi>Quick-ſands,</hi> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing more, then to ſplit ſuch veſſells in ſunder, that they may ſee, what Marchandize the inward bulke containes. Yea, it hath been the practice of ſundry Nations (and that in the perſons of Embaſſadors) vnder a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of drinking healths to their Soueraigne, firſt to drowne their wiſedome in their <hi>Graecian</hi> Cups, that afterwards they might draw, from them, that, which by
<pb facs="tcp:19401:103"/>meanes of it, was before kept ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to themſelues. And ſurelie, few or none haue euer fayled in this their enterprize; vnleſſe it were by ouer-haſtilie ſtriuing to effect that, which they ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſir'd: it hauing then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it did to <hi>Aeſops Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who gaue her henne more meat, to make her lay more egs: but it fell out otherwiſe; for, through extreame fatneſſe, ſhee ſurceaſt from laying any. And no marvaile the danger ſhould bee ſo eminent. For, <hi>Wit</hi> is not then any longer their <hi>Pilote,</hi> nor the <hi>light of Reaſon</hi> the <hi>Pole,</hi> by which their <hi>actions</hi> ſhould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducted to their wonted <hi>haven. Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Diſcretion</hi> are both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way;
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19401:103"/>which, like two firme an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chors, ſhould ſecure them in the greateſt tempeſts, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe and furious violence both of <hi>Wind,</hi> and <hi>Waue.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quid non ebrietas deſignat?</hi> ſaith the Poet; —<hi>operta recludit.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>And indeede, <hi>That which is in the heart of the ſober, is in the tongue of the drunkeard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many can with right ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that anſwer of <hi>Bias</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? who, beeing carpt at for his ſilence in a certaine banket by a fellowe, vvhoſe <hi>Wit</hi> had beene alwaies <hi>Traine-bearer</hi> to his <hi>Tongue,</hi> anſwered onelie this, that <hi>ſilence in Wine, was no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or ſigne of follie:</hi> to ſhowe
<pb facs="tcp:19401:104"/>that his taciturnitie proceeded not from any defect, as hee had falſely, and fooliſhly ſurmyzed. Surely, there are fewe, that are poſſeſt with ſo great, &amp; marvai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a moderation, &amp; that haue ſo abſolute, and powerfull a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund ouer themſelues, as this. Wherefore, let him that is wiſe, keep himſelfe from being ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken with the envenomed cups of this enchaunting, and ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bereaving <hi>Circes;</hi> vnleſſe he make light account of ruinating both himſelfe, and others.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing, are <hi>Women:</hi> who with an artificiall diſpoſing of thoſe ſeuerall beauties, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Nature,</hi> deſirous (as it were)
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19401:104"/>to ſtall foorth her treaſures, hath prodigally adorn'd them, haue made the ſpoyles of the greateſt Conquerors, trophies of their victories, and led in triumph the harts, and mindes of the wiſeſt; and that in ſuch manner, as hee that hath once ſuffred himſelfe to be captivated by the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full attractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſtarry looks, thinkes nothing to bee done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs, that is done to purchaſe, of them, euen the leaſt fauourable aſpect that may be: deeming in his fond conceit, that libertie is no where to be found, but in the incloſure of his Miſtreſſe armes. And becauſe hee thinks his tongue too weake an inſtrument to expreſſe the ſtrength, &amp; vigor
<pb facs="tcp:19401:105"/>of his affection towards her, hee makes his heart aſcend vp into his eyes, thorough which, as tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough tranſparent glaſſes, hee diſcouers vnto her, yet ſtil thinks hee diſcouers not enough, the very ſecret bed-chamber of his moſt retyred cogitations; Not remembring (ſilly wretch as hee is) that ſuch kinde of creatures, haue often-times beene made the inſtruments, to effect the downefall, and confuſion of manie: nor yet weighing vvith himſelfe, the vveakeneſſe and imbecillitie of the ſex: vvhich, as it harbours in it ſelfe a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine curious deſire to knovve all thinges, ſo is it accompanied with a kinde of careleſſe reſpect
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19401:105"/>to conceale any.</p>
            <p>They are for the moſt part, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, leaking veſſels: and like that Comike ſeruaunt, <hi>ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae rimarum, huc at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illuc effluen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi> And therefore hath the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of the Higheſt (the better to expreſſe the nature, and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſuch a one) allotted her, in the ſacred volumes of his diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi>Oracles,</hi> the name of <hi>Nacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah,</hi> from the word <hi>Nacab,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>perforare;</hi> ſhowing vs, as 't were, that ſhe is no fitter a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, then either a Siue, or a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander, to haue that infus'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, the loſſe whereof wee any thing regarde. A <hi>Romane Ladie</hi> vvas verie importunate with her husband to knowe of
<pb facs="tcp:19401:106"/>him, what ſecret matter had that day been handled in the Senate, with great oathes, and proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions neuer to reueale it: he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to try her, made vſe of his invention; tolde her that the Prieſts had ſeene a Larke flying in the ayre, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hauing a golden helmet, and a launce: and how they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted together, to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this prodigy might portend either good, or euill to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. Scarce had ſhee heard it, but preſently ſhee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed it to one of her maydes; the mayde to another of her fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes: ſo that the report was ſpred, &amp; known throughout the whole Palace, before hee came
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19401:106"/>thither himſelfe: but all of them are not made in the ſame mould. There is, ſometimes, <hi>plus virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis in ſtolâ, quàm in armis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nero,</hi> after the detection of <hi>Piſo's</hi> conſpiracie, remembring that <hi>Epicharis</hi> was likevviſe of the Faction, commaunded ſhee ſhould preſently be ſet vppon the racke; imagining, ſaith <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus, muliebre corpus impar dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> that beeing a <hi>Woman,</hi> ſhee would neuer bee able to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the paine. But all the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that either he, or his could poſſibly deuiſe, were not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to draw from her, the leaſt confeſſion of any thing, that was then obiected againſt her. The firſt dayes <hi>quaeſtion</hi> ſhe ſo vtterlie
<pb facs="tcp:19401:107"/>contemn'd, that the very chayre, in which they conveighed her from the place, did ſeeme as a Chariot, whereon ſhee rid trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing ouer the barbarous aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of their inhumane crueltie. The morrow following, beeing brought thither againe, to play her Maiſter-pryze vvith impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Tyrannie,</hi> her courage (after many rough encounters) remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo vnſhaken, that <hi>Wrath</hi> it ſelfe grew mad, to ſee the ſtroaks of an obſtinate, and vnrelenting furie, fall ſo in vaine vppon the ſofter temper of a <hi>Woman;</hi> and therevpon, did adde new vigor to the hands of her tormentors: which ſhee perceiuing, tooke a ſcarfe from about her neck, and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19401:107"/>with it (to manifeſt their weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in her fall) knits vp within her boſome the knowledge ſhee had of the fact, together with that little remainder of Spirit, vvhereof by force and violence they laboured to depriue her. <hi>Clariore exemplo</hi> (ſaith our Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian) <hi>in tanta neceſſitate alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, ac propè ignotos, protegendo, cùm viri, Senatores, &amp; equites Romani, intacti tormentis, clariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuorum pignorum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Former ages haue likewiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced a <hi>Portia,</hi> and a <hi>Leaena;</hi> the remembrance of whoſe vertue, ſhal remain for euer, as an exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary precedent to all <hi>Poſteritie.</hi> For, after her 2. louers, <hi>Armodius</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19401:108"/>and <hi>Aristogiton,</hi> hauing fayled in the execution of their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, had been put to death, ſhe was brought to the torture, to be made declare, what other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices there were of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie: but ſhe continued ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, that ſhe neuer detected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one. In reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of which fact, the <hi>Athenians</hi> cauſed a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of braſſe to be erected, which had no tongue, and placed it at the entrance of a Caſtle: ſhewing her invincible courage by the generoſitie of the beaſt; and her perſeuerance in ſecrecie, in that they made it without a tongue.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed non omne mare</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>generoſae est fertile testae.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> Euery ſoyle aboundes not with
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:19401:108"/>golden oare; nor euery channell with precious pearles: wherfore, it behooues a man to be very cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect, and wary in opening himſelfe to any of them, till ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient triall ſhall haue manifeſted the ſoundneſſe of their diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But (alas!) — <hi>quid deceat, non videt vllus amans.</hi> Avvake <hi>Samſon,</hi> the <hi>Philistins</hi> are vppon thee, ſo often repeated, was a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient <hi>aviſo</hi> of intended trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery; had not the Eye of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> with the raviſhing ſound of <hi>Dalilah's</hi> voyce, as was <hi>Argus</hi> with the delightful tunes of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curies</hi> pipe, been lull'd aſleepe in the lap of heedleſſe <hi>Senſualitie.</hi> He muſt needs tel her (ſo far had the force of her enticing tongue
<pb facs="tcp:19401:109"/>prevailed with him) wherein it was that his ſtrength conſiſted, though the hazard of his life (by revealing it) were neuer ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonie</hi> cannot chooſe, but yeelde himſelfe a priſoner in the height of his conqueſt, to the imperious lookes of <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> though the ſhamefull <hi>eclypſe</hi> of his glory, be the ſequele of his follie. <hi>Curius,</hi> to make himſelfe gratious in the eyes of his <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> will, who-ſo-euer ſaith nay, diſcloſe vnto her, the ſecret plots and practices of <hi>Catiline,</hi> though himſelfe haue as deepe a hand in them as he. The Prior of <hi>Capua,</hi> can no ſooner purpoſe any thing againſt the ſtate of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:19401:109"/>but his loue-ſick ſouldiour wil preſentlie giue notice of it to his Curtizan, &amp; ſhe to the <hi>Senate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the nature of high-aſpiring ſpirits, alwaies to affect that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, where they may bee moſt eminent: and therefore vſuallie, they make choice of <hi>Women</hi> to frequent withall; imagining that whatſoeuer they doe, or ſay, will be eſteem'd, and wondred at by them: wherevpon, to make their admiration more extreame, they wil not let to acquaint them euen with their higheſt thoughts: and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the <hi>opinion</hi> that they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd, begets a feareleſſe confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſecrecie; wherby, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they intende to doe, ſhall be diſcloſed vnto them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:110"/>
            <p>They muſt of neceſſity, now &amp; then, out of the humour of their jollities, giue vent vnto the ſmoake of their <hi>Ambition:</hi> and then, out comes that, which racks nor tortures could euer haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed. Yea, theſe are the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures their wiſdoms deeme moſt fit to impart their high-built pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes vnto; who, either for <hi>loue,</hi> or <hi>want of wit,</hi> wil willingly (they thinke) conceale, what euer they heare.</p>
            <p>But (alas!) wofull experience hath taught many, that they le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd (in ſo conceiting of them) at a wrong marke. Wherfore, let vs, with <hi>Dauid,</hi> make a couenant with our eyes; and, like <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> not vouchſafe ſo much as to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19401:110"/>glance a look vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the daughters of <hi>Darius,</hi> leaſt we be made the ſpoyle of their beautie. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the pregnant force of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is hardly to bee preſum'd vpon in this caſe. <hi>Neſcio quid la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis veneni,</hi> ſaith an ancient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>habet caro foeminea, vt pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiores citiùs corrumpat.</hi> And hence proceeded that pleaſant <hi>Motto</hi> of the Graecian Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan, in deriſion of thoſe bearded <hi>Stoïks,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui curios ſimulant,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>et Bacchanalia vivunt;</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> that in publick places ſeem to be as graue as <hi>Saturne,</hi> but in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate corners are as waggiſh as <hi>Jupiter: I know not, J,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>what bookes, what wiſdome, what
<pb facs="tcp:19401:111"/>Philoſophie; but ſure I am, ſuch manner of men knock at my gates as oft as any other.</hi> They are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in complexion: but if they be not the like in condition, let him eſteeme of them no better then of whited Sepulchers; for all this while they bee but <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchrae.</hi> They haue a face to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile the Eye, and an Eye to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch the Heart: yea, there is not any one thing in them, or about the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but is (though a ſilent, yet) a forcible Sollicitor of mans <hi>Will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Creator of all things, did frame her exquiſitlie beautifull, to pleaſe man; and the Deuill made vſe of her perfection, to deceiue him. They haue cauſed many to fall downe wounded.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19401:111"/>Prov. 7. ver. 26. and the ſtrong men are all ſlaine by them. Their lips drop as an hony-combe, and their mouth is more ſoft then Oyle: but the end of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is bitter as Wormwood, &amp; ſharp as a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edged ſword: their feet go down to death, &amp; their ſteps take hold on hel. Yea, GOD himſelfe (the ſearcher of all hearts, and who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone intuitiuelie knowes all thinges) hath euen from heauen aſſured vs, by that mirror of true wiſedom, <hi>Salomon,</hi> Prov. 6. v. 26. that the pretious life of man, is the only thing, which like blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty Tigers, they moſt eagerly hunt for: and therfore, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſt cauſe, did hee adde to their ſtile, in regarde of their
<pb facs="tcp:19401:112"/>proceedings, the attribute of <hi>ſtrange. Prov.</hi> 5.3.</p>
            <p>The Hebrew word, <hi>Zonah,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies not onely <hi>Meretrix,</hi> but withall, <hi>Caupona,</hi> and <hi>Arma:</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence we may gather the craft, and ſubtiltie of her practices, as ſhee is <hi>Meretrix,</hi> in affecting the downefall, and ouerthrowe, of ſuch as are earneſt, and deuoted followers of her ſect. Firſt, ſhe is <hi>Caupona,</hi> and then <hi>Arma.</hi> Firſt ſhe feedes, and ſatisfies their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, with the daintieſt diſhes that poſſibly ſhee can; giuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beſt entertainment, that an affected countenance &amp; geſture can affoord: but when they once draw neere the Lees, then begin they to be <hi>minus grati,</hi> leſſe wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19401:112"/>vnto her; and that for no other reaſon, <hi>quàm quòd inopiâ minus largire poſsu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> then that <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertie</hi> hath cut the wings of their former <hi>Bountie:</hi> then are her ſweete wordes converted into ſharpe ſwords; ſo that look what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhee knowes by thee, or hath at any time known fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, that ſhe thinks may procure thy ouerthrow, ſhall now be revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. She is become <hi>Arma,</hi> ſhee is become a weapon to deſtroy thee.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not, all this while, of ſuch as heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath allotted men for companions, to beguile the tediouſneſſe of this their earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pilgrimage, linking them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in loue, and vnitie, by the
<pb facs="tcp:19401:113"/>bond of an honorable &amp; lawfull <hi>Hymen:</hi> Though euen in thoſe, conſidering them as one, and the ſelfe-ſame body, it is not alwaies requiſite, that the left hand ſhold know, what the right hand doth. <hi>Seianus</hi> had no better meanes to worke the tragick ouerthrow of <hi>Druſus,</hi> who, like a dangerous rub, hind'red the ſmoother run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his ambitious thoughts, then by aſſaulting hir, whoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom he had made, as 't were, the Cabinet of his inmoſt purpoſes. For, after hee had try'd many things, <hi>promptiſſimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viſum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tacitus, ad vxore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius Livia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertere;</hi> the readieſt way he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, was to ſet vpon his wife: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſped ſo well, that, <hi>corruptâ
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19401:113"/>illâ, ſecreta eius prodebantur;</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her he had intelligence of all his ſecrets. The night it ſelfe could not ſecure him; for, euen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did ſhe obſerue his vp-ſitting, and his down-lying, leauing not ſo much as his ſighes vnregiſtred, <hi>vigili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, ſomnos, ſuſpiria patefecit:</hi> ſhee betray'd him wholly to his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. It was <hi>Eſops</hi> leſſon therfore, Commit no ſecrets to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealement of a <hi>Woman;</hi> which the Poet ſecondeth in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Crede rate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ventis; animu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne crede puellis:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nam<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> est foemineâ tutior vnda fide.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octavius Caeſar,</hi> found a want of this principle in his friende <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caenas;</hi> who, being ſomwhat more vxorious then was meete, and
<pb facs="tcp:19401:114"/>one who (as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaide of him in his Epiſtles) hauing but one wife, was married yet a thouſand times, revealed to his <hi>Terentia</hi> a ſecret, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> had imparted to him, concerning the detecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Muraena's</hi> conſpiracie; by which meanes it was ſuddainlie vented, and became of no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance. And <hi>Augustus</hi> impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this Eccho-like diſpoſition of reiterating vvhat-ſo-euer is heard, to <hi>Fulvius,</hi> as the true <hi>Symptome</hi> of a diſtempred, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled iudgement. For, hauing diſclos'd vnto him the griefe, which he conceiued, concerning the ſucceſſion of his <hi>Livia's</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the Empire, for want of iſſue of his owne; <hi>Fulvius</hi> went
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19401:114"/>and related it to his wife, and ſhe againe to <hi>Livia,</hi> who ſharply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the Emperour her husband for it: wherevpon, the morrowe after, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to ſalute him with <hi>Salvus ſis Caeſar,</hi> he was requited with <hi>Sanus ſis Fulvi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, leaſt I ſeeme an vnciuill, and ſnarling Satyriſt, in taxing (without exception) a Sex in generall, I will adde (in praiſe of ſome particulars) that ſaying of <hi>Menander,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Penu virtutis, generoſa mulier.</hi> And though neither <hi>Cato,</hi> nor <hi>Euripides</hi> were ſo fortunate, as euer to be partakers of ſo great a happineſſe, which indeed incited them to faſten thoſe vndeſerued
<pb facs="tcp:19401:115"/>imputations vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they did; yet <hi>Rubius Celer</hi> is able to avouch it, againſt the ſtrongeſt oppoſer of them all: who, as him ſelfe commaunded to be engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vppon his Monument, <hi>liv'd with Caia Ennia his wife,</hi> 43. <hi>yeres</hi> 8. <hi>monthes; and that, Sine quere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lâ:</hi> without any difference, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, or jarre.</p>
            <p>The third, and laſt thing, which is to be refrain'd, is <hi>Anger. Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus</hi> heartned <hi>Druſus</hi> againſt his brother <hi>Nero,</hi> and made him an inſtrument, to hinder him from ſucceeding <hi>Tiberius</hi> in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: yet in ſuch maner, as he did not forget to lay the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work likewiſe of his future ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw:
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19401:115"/>but hee did not ſeeme to haſten it at all; <hi>gnarus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, praeferoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et inſiaijs magis op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> knowing, as experience teacheth, that the fierceſt cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage doth alwaies lye moſt open to treacherous attempts. <hi>Fabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> therfore, notwithſtanding the provocations of his enemies, &amp; the exprobrations of his friends, who, not ſounding aright the depth of his proceedings, chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leng'd him (by reaſon of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions and delayes) of baſe &amp; ſervile cowardize, wold neuer be diverted from that courſe, which in his owne <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>iudgement,</hi> hee thought ſureſt, and fitteſt to recreate the ill-affected forces of the Empire: and indeede,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:116"/>
               <hi>ſi tantum auſus eſſet, quantum ira ſuadebat,</hi> it had vtterly been ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. For, <hi>Anger</hi> is prone to raſhneſſe; and, ſo it endanger o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, cares not for ſecuring it ſelfe. Wherefore, it were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe for any man, to imitate thoſe antient Champions, whoſe policie like to <hi>Fabius,</hi> was onely to warde the blowes of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe parties, till ſuch time as they perceiued their ſtrength in aſſaulting to be well-nigh ſpent; neuer vſing to ſtrike, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, when wrath perſwaded them, but when <hi>Occaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The wakefull Eye of <hi>Reaſon</hi> muſt continually keepe <hi>Centinel</hi> ouer his Paſſions: and ſetled <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> muſt be the <hi>Fort,</hi> that muſt
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19401:116"/>protect him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the furious bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of all incenſing, and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſturbing ſpeeches whatſoeuer. They are charmes of a cunning Charmer: againſt which, if (like the wiſer Adder) he ſtop not his eare, his vtter ruine cannot chuſe but inſtantly follow. For they are vſed, either to avert him from ſome courſe hee hath alreadie vndertaken, which in the end, beeing thoroughly followed, would proue prejudiciall to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as by the fore-alledged example of <hi>Fabius,</hi> may bee eaſily diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; or to vrge-him thereby, to manifeſt ſom part of his moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, &amp; private thoughts: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Poet being nothing igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, dooth moſt elegantly call
<pb facs="tcp:19401:117"/>
               <hi>Paſſions, tortures;</hi> whereby men are vrged, and enforced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their ſecrets:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hor. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtl. lib.</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 18.</note>
               <q>
                  <hi>— Et vino tortus, et irâ.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>Tiberius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Annal.</hi> 4.</note> who, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> reports, <hi>nullam aequè ex virtutibus ſuis, quàm diſſimulationem diligebat,</hi> feeling him-ſelfe ſtung with a ſharpe invectiue of <hi>Agrippina,</hi> concerning the accuſation of <hi>Claudia Pulchra,</hi> her Coſen ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, came a ſtep foorth of his diſſimulation, when he ſaid, <hi>You are hurt, becauſe you do not raigne.</hi> Of which, our Hiſtorian ſaith: <hi>Audita haec raram occulti pectoris vocem elicuêre, correptam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co verſu admonuit, ideo laedi, quia non regnaret.</hi> And <hi>Catiline, qui
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:19401:117"/>ad omnia diſſimulanda paratus,</hi> did likewiſe erre in this. For, had he proſecuted his firſt deſſigne (which was, with an outward and forced apparance of true humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, expreſſed by the liuelieſt characters hee could, both in his geſture, countenance, and wordes, to daſh the accuſations of his Adverſaries, and to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate him-ſelfe into the loue, and fauour of the Senate) hee might peradventure (hauing freed him-ſelfe by this meanes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſiniſter conceite of theirs) eaſilie haue effected his purpoſe. But, when hee heard thoſe odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous titles of Enemie, and Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, caſt vppon him by the full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd multitude, then <hi>Quia
<pb facs="tcp:19401:118"/>circumventus ab inimicis praeceps agor, incendium meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ruinâ extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guam</hi> muſt needes diſcouer the marke of his diſordinate <hi>Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and make knowne vnto the world, what maſſacrous, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious thoughts, had (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his ſmooth external car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage) anchred in his boſom.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, let euery man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour, by all meanes poſſible, to calme, and allay, thoſe ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, and tempeſtuous motions of the mind; &amp; to be that which few are, ſo true to himſelfe, and ſo ſetled, that at no time, either vpon heat, or vpon braverie, or vpon kindneſſe (as I ſhew'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) or vpon trouble of minde, and weakeneſſe, hee open him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19401:118"/>or ſuffer his tongue to eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate any part of his thoughts: no, not though he ſhould be put to it by a <hi>Counter-diſſimulation;</hi> which is a faſhion of enquiry, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie currant with many, who will not ſtick, according to the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Adage, <hi>Dezir mentira, para ſacar verdad;</hi> to tell a lye, for to extort a truth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:119"/>
            <head>Of Reputation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing more hard, and difficult to com by, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a true &amp; certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the inward diſpoſition, and abilities of man. His mind is ſubiect to many ſecret inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: 't is like a Labyrinth, full of crooked windings, &amp; turnings. His deedes, wordes, &amp; geſtures,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19401:119"/>are neuer lightlie beautified, but with ſome outward impoſture: they are fraught with vanitie, and deceite: and, like that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Figge-tree in the Goſpel, doe make a glorious floriſh, but affoord no fruite.</p>
            <p>The ſillie Sheepe (ſaide <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chidamas</hi>) can neuer change his naturall voyce: but man can alter, and faſhion his, to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeuerall, and ſundry Dialects, as he pleaſe, till ſuch time as his Ambition haue attain'd to that, which it deſired.</p>
            <p>Some haue beene thought vvoorthie of advauncement, ſaue vvhen they had it: and ſome againe, haue purchaſt to them-ſelues good reputation,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:120"/>and been well eſteemed in place of <hi>Greatneſse,</hi> which before were otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>It hath beene often ſeene, that ſuch as became a meaner part well, haue failed in a greater, and diſgraced it. Hence was it that <hi>Galba, maior privato viſus, dum privatus fuit, et omnium conſenſu capax imperij, niſi imperaſſet:</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee was a private ſubject, did ſeeme to out-runne the meane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his fortune; and, by a generall conſent of all men, was thought worthy to rule, if he had neuer ruled: whereas, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary was bruted of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſpaſian,</hi> to wit, that, <hi>omnium ante ſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum in melius mutatus,</hi> of all the Princes that euer did precede
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:19401:120"/>him, he alone was changed to the better: which may bee likewiſe inſtanced vpon the Son of <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingbrooke,</hi> entitled after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe of his Father, <hi>Henry</hi> the fift of England. <hi>Ignorance,</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is of too dull an apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to cenſure aright the nature of mens actions. Shee depriueth <hi>Reaſon</hi> of her diſcurſiue facultie, and frames her iudgement, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the illiterate verdict, that ouward <hi>Senſe</hi> giues of them. And hence commeth it often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that many are reputed wiſe, and valiant, who, were the ground of their ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceited me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit well examined, would ſeeme the contrary. <hi>True Valour</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not in being deſperatly ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous.
<pb facs="tcp:19401:121"/>It is not the loue of vertue, but the hate of life, that makes men ſo. <hi>Antigonus</hi> had a Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, whoſe forwardnes vpon any dangerous ſeruice he much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired; and therfore hauing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode, that hee was troubled with an Impoſtume in his bodie, gaue his Chirurgians expreſſe commaund to ſee him diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie cured: which done, <hi>Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> perceiued, that hee ſhewed not himſelfe ſo valiant as he was wont, &amp; therevpon rebuk't him for it: but the Souldiour anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, that hee might blame himſelfe; for it was hee, that had made him leſſe hardie then hee was before, in cauſing him to bee cured of thoſe ills, which had
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:19401:121"/>made him altogether careleſſe of his life. And hither may that ſpeech of the <hi>Sibaritans,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Lacedaemonians</hi> auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer kind of living, be well refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: <hi>That it was no maruell, they ſought for death ſo furiouſly in the warres, conſidering how labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and ſtrict a life, they did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure at home:</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Rebus in anguſtis facile eſt contemnere vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </q> And therefore, that <hi>Reputation</hi> which is purchaſt this way, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be of any long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. It is a vapour, drawne out of the earthy boſome of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> which, where the rayes of cleerer <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> do ſhine out, is ſuddenly diſperſed. True Vertue is alwaies like her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:122"/>ſhe ſquares with euery ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, and keeps a iuſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in all her actions. Shee will not feare to die, as <hi>Cato</hi> did, though <hi>Caeſar</hi> were her deereſt friend. Such therefore, as beeing in the prime, and flower of their youth, doe ſeeme content with euery breath of honor; and, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they haue gain'd ſome little reputation in the world, betake themſelues immediatly vpon it, to a retyred life, confining their ſo begunne fortune, within the bounds of ſome ſolitary Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: it is to bee ſuſpected, they were generous but onely in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, and that the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and diſtruſt of their owne weakeneſſe, made them
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:19401:122"/>withdraw themſelues from acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leaſt by their vnſufficient ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of matters, they might happelie loſe that accidentall glory, which vpon no certaine principles they had formerlie got. For, honour ſerues but as a ſawee, to whet the appetite of thoſe, whoſe hearts are firme, &amp; of a noble, and vnyeelding tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. It is a gale, which beares the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeedilie to the vndertaking of euery haughtie enterprize. The prayſe of hauing well conducted the courſe of one, is a bayte, which drawes them on to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-going of another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hercules,</hi> in his trauailes, vvil not leaue ſo much as <hi>Hell</hi> vnvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited: but euen vppon the gates
<pb facs="tcp:19401:123"/>thereof, will ſtriue to erect a tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy to his triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phant merit. Yea, in military matters, the report of any one thing valorouſly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, eſpecially vpon the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of an imployment, is that, which makes a ſmooth, and eaſie paſſage for future attempts. It is a meanes to driue the wauering affection of ambiguous friendes to a certaine ſtand, and to bring forth an encreaſe of loue in the harts, and mindes of ſuch, as are firme, and loyall. It works a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Obedience</hi> in thy whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and procures thee meanes, and munition, with ſtore of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther warlike neceſſaries from thy friendes and allyes, &amp; that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paine &amp; trouble to thy ſelfe;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19401:123"/>For, whil'ſt euery one contends to bee thought a meanes in the rayſing of thy tranſcending for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, thy worth cannot poſſibly want ladders by which to climbe. And therefore <hi>Domitius Corbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> at his firſt comming to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of <hi>Armenia,</hi> endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to doe ſomewhat, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> reports, <hi>vt famae inſerviret,</hi> that in thoſe parts might purchaſe him the credit, and reputation of ſufficiencie; which in nevve buſineſſes is moſt availeable. And <hi>Iulius Agricola,</hi> at his firſt arriuall into <hi>Brittaine,</hi> carried himſelfe in the like manner, <hi>non ignarus instandum famae, ac pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vt prima ceſſiſsent, fore vniverſa;</hi> that fame was to bee follovved,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:124"/>and as he ſped in the firſt, ſuch it was likely would his ſucceſſe be in the reſt. But it is heer, as it is in meates: if taken immoderat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (though they be neuer ſo nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing) they proue a burthen to the body, rather then otherwiſe. It is requiſite therefore, that wee ſometimes clip the wings of our <hi>Reputation,</hi> and not ſuffer them to growe beyond the compaſſe of our neaſt.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inſani ſapiens nomen ferat, aequus iniqui,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vltra qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſatis eſt, virtute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſi petat ipſam.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> The wiſer ſort will of their owne accord, a little now and then, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their worth, by ſtripping themſelues awhile of all imployments. They know there is nothing loſt, by making
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19401:124"/>themſelues (for a time) leſſe then they are. Ouermuch <hi>Estimation</hi> hath bin the bane of many. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibiades,</hi> by reaſon of the ſundry great exploytes he had atchiued in the behalfe of his Country, had got ſo great an opinion of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie,</hi> that when hee fayled in the due performance of anie thing, hee was preſently ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: euery one was apt to iudge, that it was not, bicauſe he could not doe it, but becauſe he would not; and that where-ſoeuer hee was minded to imploy himſelfe, nothing could poſſibly eſcape him.</p>
            <p>Hence likewiſe was it, that <hi>Iohn Guicciardine</hi> vvas accuſed to haue beene corrupted by thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:19401:125"/>of <hi>Lucca,</hi> becauſe hee fayled in the expugnation of their Cittie. The ſafeſt way therefore to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our ſelues from danger, is to attire our worthineſſe in ſuch manner, as it may ſtill bee the ſame it was in inward ſubſtance; onely altred, and diſguis'd a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in outward ſhowe.</p>
            <p>It is reported of <hi>Poppaeus Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tac. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib.</hi> 6.</note> that for the ſpace of 24. yeeres, and that in the dayes of tyrannie, he was ſtill made Ruler ouer the greateſt Prouinces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Empire, <hi>nullam ob eximiam artem,</hi> not for any excellent ability that was in him; <hi>Sed quòd par negotijs, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuprà erat;</hi> but that his ſufficiencie did no more then equall the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:19401:125"/>charge, vvhich was impoſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him. And to ſpeak plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, VViſemen, in the choyce of inſtruments, are ſildome wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to make vſe of ſuch, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of importance, vvhoſe cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning iudgement, they thinke can ſounde the depth of their intent, or, out of their imployments, contriue any thing whereby to grace themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Agricola</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tacitus</hi>) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his many ſeruices done to the Empire, <hi>Nunquam in ſuam famam gestis exſultavit,</hi> did neuer boaſt of any action to his owne fame; but (as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Planet) did modeſtly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the light he had, to be
<pb facs="tcp:19401:126"/>wholly deriued from a higher Sunne: thus did hee ſteale from Envie, and not defraude himſelfe of his deſerued glory. <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus</hi> likewiſe, hauing calmed &amp; alayed the tumultuous broyles, &amp; inſurrections of the <hi>Germans,</hi> cauſed a pyle of weapons to be raiſed, with this ſtately title; DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BELLATIS, INTER RHENVM ALBIMQVE NATIONIBVS, EXERCITVM TIBERII CAE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SARIS EA MONIMENTA MARTI, ET IOVI, ET AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTO SACRAVISSE. <hi>That the Nations betweene Rhene, and Albis beeing ouercome, Tiberius Caeſars Armie had conſecrated thoſe Moniments to Mars, Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Auguſtus:</hi> but added no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:19401:126"/>of himſelfe, <hi>metu invidiae,</hi> for fear that either Envie or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, might find a ſubiect in him, for their malicious, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venom'd teeth to gnawe vppon: or thinking (as it is) the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a well-done deed, to be a ſufficient recompence for the dooing it. And this it was that kept them vpright, amidſt the ruines of ſo many Woorthies, in thoſe vnworthy times.</p>
            <p>But (alas!) the high-erected thoughts of an ambitious heart, cannot poſſibly bee brought to conceiue the meaning of this principle. They will alwaies ſaile by the Carde and Compaſſe of their own mind; and rather then yeelde in their popular depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:127"/>their entertainments, gifts, or publike grace, moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully hazarde the diſtaſte of all men. <hi>Caeſar</hi> careth for nothing, but the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his deſſignes; his ſpirit is beyond the reach of feare. If the Sea ſwell in waues to let his paſſage to <hi>Brunduſium:</hi> hee ſwells againe in wordes, and bids the Mariner, Saile on, <hi>Thou carriest Caeſar, and his Fortunes with thee.</hi> And indeed, his <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi> was the onely thing, that kept both him, &amp; his eſtate from beeing ſhaken, and disjoynted, by the violent events of ſuch reſolved courſes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:19401:127"/>
            <head>Of Accuſation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is no golden age in which we liue; but an age ſo corrupted, &amp; depraved, that in compariſon of others, many are eſteemed vertuous, at a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable rate. Yea, hee is thought to doe good enough, who, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is in place of authoritie, doth but little ill.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:128"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Iampridem equidem rerum voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula amiſimus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Salluſt: bello Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til.</note> 
               <hi>quia bona aliena largire, liberalitas; malarum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum audacia, fortitudo vocatur.</hi> All thinges haue vndergone an alteration, both in name and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Simplicitie</hi> hath principled her ſelfe with ſtronger <hi>Axiomes</hi> then heeretofore, &amp; hath learn'd to ſquare and order the vvhole courſe of her converſation by an other kinde of Methode, then that ſhee practiced during the harmleſſe infancie of the World. The ſilly Dove hath beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, for her owne ſecuritie, to ioyne in friendſhip with the Serpent: and the Lyon thinks it no diſparagement, to caſe his valour (if neede require) vnder
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:19401:128"/>the out-ſide of the ſubtile Fox. For, <hi>Pietie</hi> now is counted but a fantaſticke fiction: and <hi>Vpright-dealing,</hi> but an aierie apparition. True vertuous actions, are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeene vpon the Scene, but when by the neceſſitie of Lawes, they are enforced to ſhow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. For, where election a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds, and that all libertie may be vs'd, euery thing is preſently brought to a moſt irregular, and confuſed motion. The <hi>Will</hi> of man is ſo perverted, that <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> is ſildome made the ſcope of his deſſignes.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Catiline,</hi> that when he wanted preſent matter for his miſchieuous mind to worke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, hee was no way ſcrupulous
<pb facs="tcp:19401:129"/>to circumvent, and kill, <hi>inſontes, ſicuti ſontes,</hi> thoſe that had neuer purchaſt his hatefull fury by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending him, as well as others: and leaſt either his hart, or hand, might happely wex numme, for want of imployment, <hi>gratuitò potiùs malus, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> crudelis erat,</hi> hee would be voluntarily cruell, and without expectance of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>And what was ſaide of him, I feare mee, may be too truly iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in many. For (alas!) the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of a vertuous deede, is too weak a motiue to incite our dull affections to the dooing of it. Tis eyther hope of <hi>Reward,</hi> or feare of <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> that in the attempt of thinges, orders,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:19401:129"/>and directs our choyce. Giue way but to <hi>Impunitie,</hi> and yee ſhall ſee how <hi>Vncivilitie,</hi> like a ravening <hi>Deluge,</hi> will (on the ſuddaine) waſh away the print, and forme of all <hi>Mortalitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Non ſum moechus</hi>—</q>
            <p>I am not an Adulterer, ſaith one;</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ego hercule fur, vbi vaſa</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Praetereo ſapiens argentea.</hi>—</l>
            </q>
            <p>But, as the Satyriſt affirmes in the verſes following,
<q>
                  <l>— <hi>tolle perîclum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iam vaga proſiliet fraenis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>natura remotis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:130"/>
            <p>So that, for the better orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and preſeruing of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, 't is very requiſite, there ſhould be ſuch Miniſters appointed in it, as may without reſpect, or partialitie, giue <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> information of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar proceedings of private men. For, by this meanes, eyther the feare of beeing accuſed, will curbe their ambitious purpoſes, and keepe them from attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing againſt the libertie of that State, in which they liue: or, hauing attempted, the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation it ſelfe will preſently ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them. Beſides, it will giue ayre enough for the venting foorth of thoſe peſtiferous tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours &amp; inflammations, which
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:19401:130"/>thorough hatred, or emulation, are bred in the crazie mindes of ill-affected perſons. Yea, there is nothing, that can more firmelie ſettle and eſtabliſh a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, then to order it in ſuch manner, that the alteration of thoſe humors, which do trauaile and moleſt it, may find a <hi>Recipe</hi> at home, for her recouerie, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the <hi>Lawe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, if at any time wee ſee, that in the diviſions, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions of an vnſetled <hi>Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace,</hi> either partie ſhal haue neede to ranke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with forraine correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, the cauſe heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may lawfully be ſuſpected to proceed from ſome manifeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the inſtitution of that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.
<pb facs="tcp:19401:131"/>But, if with vs (as heere-to-fore in <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſuch like Popular and Democraticall Polities of elder times, <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Malice</hi> were authoriſed, either by <hi>Ostraciſme,</hi> or any other ſuch ſpecious kinde of proceedings, to top the branches of a ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Vertue, there ſhould not an <hi>Ariſtides</hi> breathe amongſt vs, but euery baſe, and illiterate groome, wold ſtriue (not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing why perhaps) to procure his baniſhment.</p>
            <p>Nothing can ſcape the forked tongue of Detraction. Slaunder, we ſee, did faſten her envenom'd teeth vpon the pretious body of our Sauior <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, &amp; gaue him not ouer vntil death; yet was
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:19401:131"/>his nature no way ſo imperfect, as to offend. It was the advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Medius,</hi> a damnable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter, in the court of <hi>Alex. That a man ſhold not ſpare to bite the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of any one, with vntruths &amp; forged accuſations: for, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>the hurt may happely be cur'd, the ſcar yet wil ſtil remain.</hi> And what ſucceſſe did followe vpon the practice of this his dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may eaſily be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer'd in the fall of <hi>Calliſthenes, Parmenio,</hi> &amp; <hi>Philotas.</hi> Wiſdome therefore &amp; moderation, ſhould continually ſit in the eares of <hi>Greatnes,</hi> &amp; there moſt carefully diſtinguiſh betweene <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Falſhood,</hi> between a lawful accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and that which is fained.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:132"/>
            <p>It was an eaſie matter (conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the ſuſpicious nature of <hi>Tiberius</hi>) for <hi>Caepio Criſpinus,</hi> who (as <hi>Tacitus</hi> reports) by humou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his bloody mind, with cloſe, and ſcandalous delations, had ſet a golden outſide vppon his formerlie dejected and ragged fortunes, to call the life of <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie</hi> it ſelfe in queſtion. Hee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrewe <hi>Marcellus,</hi> by accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him to haue ſpoken ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſiniſterly of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> which then (ſaith our Hiſtorian) was accounted an inevitable crime; by reaſon that the Accuſer did (by continuall obſeruing) ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the vicious carriage, and diſpoſition of the Prince, whatſoeuer was moſt vile, &amp; apt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:19401:132"/>to be reproch't, and vpon that did frame and faſhion his Indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, <hi>Nam quia vera erant, etiam dicta credeba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur.</hi> For, euery thing was prone to bee belieued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 't was knowne to be deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. But, howſoeuer barbarous and inhumane Tyrants, may thinke by countenauncing ſuch Sycophants, to ſecure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and their eſtates; yet milder Princes will warily avoyd them. Ambitious <hi>Vſurpation,</hi> hath bin ſeene to cut the throat of lawfull <hi>Soueraigntie,</hi> and (afterwards) to ſeate it ſelfe by this meanes, in the chayre of Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>K. <hi>Richards</hi> baniſhing of <hi>Mow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bray,</hi> vpon the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene him &amp; <hi>Bullingbrooke,</hi> was
<pb facs="tcp:19401:133"/>his owne depoſing. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentinian</hi> II. hauing cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Aetius</hi> to be executed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded afterwards of <hi>Proximus,</hi> how he approov'd the fact: who anſwered, that he knew not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee had lawfully put him to death, or no; but ſure hee was, that by ſo dooing, with his owne left hand, he had cut off his right. Which happ'ned ſhortly after to be very true; for he was ſlaine by <hi>Maximus,</hi> a <hi>Romane Patrician,</hi> whoſe treacherous attempts, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the life of <hi>Aetius,</hi> were ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-aw'd, that they durſt neuer offer ſo much as once to ſhowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. <hi>Alexander</hi> had depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved himſelfe of a true &amp; faithfull Phyſician, if he had ſuffered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:19401:133"/>to be led away with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, and iealouſies of others. Tis therefore requiſite, ſome exemplarie puniſhments ſhould be inflicted vppon thoſe, that ſpightfully endevour to ſoyle, and blacke, the reputation of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, with the filthy ſlime of their malicious and viperous iawes. For, otherwiſe, the ſillie Lambe ſhall neuer drinke at the fountaine, but the greedy Wolfe will accuſe him without cauſe, and deuoure him without lawe.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>Haman</hi> hang vpon the gallowes, vvhich by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was erected for the death of Innocencie: let thoſe ranke and Goatiſh-eyed Elders, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-goe that cruell ſentence,
<pb facs="tcp:19401:134"/>which their vnſatisfied <hi>Lust,</hi> had wickedly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>triv'd againſt a ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>Chastitie.</hi> Finally, let the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> be quit; &amp; thoſe, which falſely did accuſe him, be condemned by <hi>Darius</hi> to the Lyons den.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> n. Lex iuſtior vlla est,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> necis artifices arte perire ſuâ.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19401:134"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
